<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Poimnē phylakion, The pastors charge and the peoples duty a sermon (for the most part) preached at the Assembly of ministers at Exon, June 7, 1693 / by Samuel Stoddon.</title>
            <author>Stoddon, Samuel.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1694</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 186 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 87 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A61666</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S5714</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R645</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12625896</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12625896</idno>
            <idno type="VID">64639</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A61666)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 64639)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 336:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Poimnē phylakion, The pastors charge and the peoples duty a sermon (for the most part) preached at the Assembly of ministers at Exon, June 7, 1693 / by Samuel Stoddon.</title>
                  <author>Stoddon, Samuel.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 162 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Jonath. Robinson ... and are to be sold by Robert Osborne ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1694.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Title transliterated from Greek.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  John XXI, 15-17 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:64639:1"/>
            <p>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> The Paſtors Charge, AND THE Peoples Duty.</p>
            <p>A SERMON (for the moſt part) Preached at the <hi>Aſſembly of Miniſters</hi> AT EXON, June 7. 1693.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Samuel Stoddon.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Ezek.</hi> 34.2.</bibl>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Jonath. Robinſon</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-yard; and are to be ſold by <hi>Robert Osborne</hi> Bookſeller in <hi>Exon.</hi> 1694.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:64639:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:64639:2"/>
            <head>TO My Reverend and Dearly Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved Brethren, the United Miniſters of Chriſt in the County of <hi>Devon;</hi> Grace and Peace in, and from our our LORD Jeſus Chriſt.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reverend Brethren,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IN compliance with your Affectio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate <hi>Importunity,</hi> and Obedience to your Acknowledged <hi>Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity,</hi> I now humbly offer you, what few others in the World, but your ſelves could have wreſted from me. I confeſs it hath always been accounted an <hi>Ill Omen,</hi> when the <hi>Victim</hi> comes unwillingly to the <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar:</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:64639:3"/>But Conſcience can avouch this for me, That I have not come un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willingly to any Work, wherein I have had a proſpect of ſerving the glorious Ends of my Miniſtry. 'Twas your <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nanimous <hi>Vote,</hi> that laid the Injunction of this Pulpit-work upon me; to which (though conſcious of my own <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nfitneſs) I readily enough yielded. But when, after my utmoſt Endeavours to prevent it, you ſo ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſiſtibly deſired its Publication, I could not but be troubled. Yet not from any ſullen Averſion to the <hi>Preſs,</hi> as the Over-modeſt Humour of ſome is, that are eminently better quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied to ſerve the Churches of Chriſt that way; but from the unprepared<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the <hi>Diſcourſe</hi> for Publick View, and the little Time or Strength that I have to fit it better.</p>
            <p>It being, for the moſt part, <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo ad Clerum;</hi> and willing to ſpeak a little, as I could, to what my <hi>Text</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:64639:3"/>ſo naturally directed me to, I took the liberty to offer you the bare <hi>Skeliton,</hi> without thoſe Exegetical or Inculcative Enlargements, which, in a ruder Auditory, might have been more neceſſary.</p>
            <p>Wherefore now (not without your leave) I preſume to preſent it both to <hi>You,</hi> and to the <hi>World,</hi> in a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond <hi>Edition,</hi> with a few, and but a few <hi>Additions,</hi> and neceſſary <hi>Varia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions;</hi> whether for the better or the worſe, I cannot tell. I did once hope to have buried it in the faithful <hi>Ears</hi> and <hi>Hearts</hi> of my then preſent Auditors, and never have concerned my <hi>Pen</hi> any further about it. But ſeeing it is your pleaſure to ſend it further abroad, you have made your ſelves Sponſors with me, for all the Infirmities and Faults of it; and have given me the Confidence now, to <hi>Claim</hi> the concurrence of your Prayers; That God will pardon the many <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:64639:4"/>and proſper the good <hi>Deſign</hi> of it; to his own Glory, and the Spiritual Good of all thoſe, into whoſe hands it ſhall come. And which is the fervent Deſire of,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your unworthy Brother and Fellow-Servant in the Goſpel of Chriſt, S. S.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Sidbury,</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>Auguſt</hi> 15. 1693.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:64639:4"/>
            <head>THE Paſtor's Charge, AND The Peoples Duty.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>John 21.15, 16, 17.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <l>— Feed my Lambs.</l>
                  <l>— Feed my Sheep.</l>
                  <l>— Feed my Sheep.</l>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CAP. I.</hi> The Text opened.</head>
               <p>MY Reverend and Dear Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren! Unto us theſe words are ſpoken; unto whom they were firſt, and immediately directed; by whom; on what occaſion; and with what Argument they are enforced, I need not tell you: The bare Reading
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:64639:5"/>theſe three Verſes at length, will make all this plain and obvious to the meaneſt Underſtanding.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>So when they had dined, Jeſus ſaith to</hi> Simon Peter, Simon, <hi>Son of</hi> Jonas, <hi>lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt thoume more than theſe? He ſaith unto him; yea LORD; thou knoweſt I that love thee. He ſaith unto him; Feed my Lambs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>He ſaith to him again the ſecond time;</hi> Simon, <hi>Son of</hi> Jonas, <hi>lovest thou me? He ſaith unto him; yea LORD; thou knoweſt that I love thee. He ſaith unto him; Feed my Sheep.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>He ſaith unto him the third time;</hi> Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, <hi>Son of</hi> Jonas; <hi>loveſt thou me?</hi> Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>was grieved becauſe he ſaid unto him the third time; loveſt thou me? And he ſaid unto him, LORD, thou knoweſt all things; thou knoweſt that I love thee: Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus ſaith unto him; Feed my Sheep.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>You ſee 'twas our LORD Jeſus Chriſt, the great <hi>Shepherd</hi> of the <hi>Sheep,</hi> and whoſe <hi>Own</hi> they are, that ſpake theſe words with his own mouth, and
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:64639:5"/>left this thrice inculcated <hi>Charge</hi> with his Diſciple <hi>Peter,</hi> unto whom in the name of all the reſt, he was wont to direct his ſpeeches, not as <hi>Princeps,</hi> but as<note n="*" place="margin">This notion will need a little explica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in a more proper place.</note> 
                  <hi>Primus A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtolorum;</hi> and with whom, all the other, not only of his then preſent Brethren; but of all their future Succeſſors in the ſame Office, were included. And this after his Reſurrection from the Grave, wherein he had paid the full Price of our Redemption; and having laid down his Life for his <hi>Sheep,</hi> had vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctoriouſly triumphed over his and their laſt Enemy <hi>Death,</hi> and was now about to leave the World, and go to the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. And knowing that he muſt leave his poor <hi>Flock,</hi> whom he had purchaſed at ſo dear a Rate, in the midſt of the <hi>Wolves</hi> and wild Beaſts of this <hi>Wilderneſs;</hi> he thus charges his Servants concerning them, unto whom he committed the Care and Over-ſight of them; <hi>Feed my Lambs; Feed my Sheep.</hi> And, leſt this ſhould be too little, he ſtrengthens his <hi>Charge</hi> with the moſt obliging Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that could poſſibly be urg'd;
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:64639:6"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:64639:6"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:64639:7"/>
                  <hi>Loveſt thou me?</hi> And this three times repeated; which argues an extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Earneſtneſs, and particular Emphaſis, that he would put upon it. There are ſome, that think this was three times repeated in perſonal reflection on <hi>Peter,</hi> for his thrice denying him; and perhaps there may be ſomething in that: But what was ſaid to <hi>Peter,</hi> was ſaid to all the <hi>Reſt,</hi> both <hi>Them</hi> and <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s;</hi> and his thrice repeating it, was but to let us know, how dear his little <hi>Flock</hi> was to him; what Jealouſie he had for them, leſt they ſhould be neglected; and what an Account he will require of us concerning them in the Day of our Accounts.</p>
               <p>And here, if I may not be thought too curiouſly to criticize upon the <hi>Text,</hi> I would obſerve theſe two things in it.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>The Order Of the Charge.</item>
                  <item>The Matter Of the Charge.</item>
               </list>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>The Order.</hi> We ſee the <hi>Lambs</hi> are firſt mentioned, then the <hi>Sheep.</hi> Though theſe Names are ſometimes, in Scripture,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:64639:7"/>promiſcuouſly uſed; yet in propriety of ſpeech, there is a difference, though not of <hi>Kind,</hi> yet of <hi>Age</hi> at leaſt; and the Terms are not convertible. Though all <hi>Lambs</hi> are <hi>Sheep,</hi> all <hi>Sheep</hi> are not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly called <hi>Lambs.</hi> And where we find both words uſed, as in the <hi>Text,</hi> it plainly intimates a diſtribution of the <hi>Flock</hi> into theſe two conſtituting parts of it.</p>
               <p>By the <hi>Lambs</hi> here, I underſtand on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly what the plain uſe of the <hi>Metaphor</hi> directs to; <hi>viz.</hi> the Younger ſort; Younger, either in reſpect of <hi>Years,</hi> or in reſpect of <hi>Grace.</hi> And why are theſe firſt mentioned? Some uſe may be made of this; though not that uſe, which <hi>Bellarmine</hi> fooliſhly and falſly ſuggeſts. But they may be firſt nam'd in our LORD's Charge to us.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Becauſe they are the <hi>weaker part</hi> of the Flock; which doth by ſo much the more recommend them to our ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dereſt Care and Inſpection: They are worſt able to defend, or provide for themſelves; they are weak in Judgment, and weak in Experience; and weak things are ſoon loſt. Therefore eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:64639:8"/>proviſion muſt be made for them.</p>
               <p n="2">2. They are firſt in the <hi>Charge,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are firſt in the <hi>Order of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</hi> They are <hi>Lambs</hi> before they are Sheep; and herein they ſeem to claim a precedency. Therefore firſt, <hi>Feed my Lambs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. They are <hi>Spes Gregis; The Hope of the Flock.</hi> Though the weaker, yet commonly the ſounder part; though the more Ignorant, yet the more Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able. O Sirs! if we loſe them while they are <hi>Lambs,</hi> 'twill be hard, perhaps too late to cure or recover them, when they are grown more wild, or more rotten. The greateſt hope of the ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs of our work lies here. But where common Experience ſays ſo much, I need ſay the leſs.</p>
               <p n="4">4. They are <hi>Fundamentum Gregis.</hi> By whom the Stock is maintained, and a Succeſſion preſerved in the Earth. The <hi>Seminary</hi> and common <hi>Fund</hi> of the Church. To loſe the Lambs, is the ready way to loſe all.</p>
               <p n="5">5. They are the moſt <hi>Innocent</hi> part of the Flock. There is a kind of <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, an innate Principle of Dearneſs
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:64639:8"/>and Affection in every ingenuous Breaſt for ſuch as theſe. <hi>Can a Woman forget her ſucking Child?</hi> She will ſooner for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get all the reſt, than her Little one. <hi>He ſhall feed his Flock like a Shepherd; he ſhall gather the Lambs with his arm, and carry them in his boſom, and ſhall gently lead thoſe that are with young, Iſa.</hi> 40.11. This was ſpoken of <hi>Him,</hi> by whom the words of my Text were ſpoken. No wonder then that he takes the firſt care for theſe. Yet though the <hi>Lambs</hi> are firſt, we find them but once mentioned in the Text; but the <hi>Sheep</hi> twice. Is it becauſe the <hi>Sheep</hi> are more in number, or more in value? or doth it not ſeem rather to tell us; That though the <hi>Lambs</hi> call for our firſt Care; the <hi>Sheep</hi> are they that coſt us double Labour? while they are young and tender, they are more ductile, and teachable; their Minds are a <hi>Tabula raſa,</hi> not prepoſſeſt with Opinion or Prejudice; their Affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions green and complying, and not actually preingag'd; their Conſciences untoucht in their natural Virginity: I do not ſay in their Original Purity. But when they are grown up, and have
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:64639:9"/>imbib'd a few Religious Notions, and are grown fond of them; or have proſelyted themſelves to a Party; how hard is it convince them, or to rectifie their Errours in Judgment? When they have taſted the ſenſual ſweets of ſin; or intangled their hearts in the Cares of the World, or eſpouſed their Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Profeſſion to a Carnal Intereſt; or, under a Form of Godlineſs, are come to ſettle in their <hi>Lees;</hi> O how hard, and next to impoſſible is it then to move them? when ſtray'd among the wild Beaſts, to reclaim them? when rotten, to recover them? Here's double Labour with theſe.</p>
               <p>Or elſe they are twice mentioned, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are capable of Paſtoral In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpection, in one point beyond what the Lambs are. Of which I ſhall take a little notice in the next. Thus much for the <hi>Order</hi> of the Charge.</p>
               <p n="2">2. We are next to conſider the <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> of it: Wherein I ſhall not uſe the old Logical Terms of dividing; but briefly take notice of the <hi>Charge</hi> it ſelf; and the <hi>Argument,</hi> that is here uſed to enforce it.</p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:64639:9"/>
               <p n="1">1. The <hi>Gharge</hi> is; <hi>Feed my Lambs, and my Sheep.</hi> My Lambs, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. My Sheep, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. I would not <hi>querere nodum in Scirpo,</hi> ſeek for Subtilties, where the Text neither intends, nor needs any. I know the words are often ſynonymouſly uſed; yet if we look into their <hi>Etymo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy,</hi> we ſhall find ſome difference; and which, to me, ſeems to be deſigned here; <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſignifies only <hi>to feed,</hi> ſo as to make fat, <hi>ſaginare;</hi> but <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, is not only <hi>to ſeed,</hi> but <hi>to rule and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern;</hi> to exerciſe the Office; not only the Care, but the Power of a Shepherd over his Flock. So then, here's the Reaſon of what I juſt now hinted at. The <hi>Lambs</hi> are but once mentioned; and the Charge concerning them is only to <hi>Feed</hi> them; theſe being not ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of Paſtoral Diſcipline and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. But with the <hi>Sheep,</hi> there's the double labour, both of <hi>Feeding and Ruling.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I ſhall not now trouble you with the <hi>Popiſh</hi> Queſtions, that have been controverted on this Text, as being alien to the deſign and proper work
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:64639:10"/>of this Day. Only let me ſay again; That what was here ſpoken to <hi>Peter,</hi> was ſpoken to every one of the other Apoſtles; wherein both They, and We. that have ſucceeded them in their ordinary Work and Office of the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry, are perſonally and equally con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned. And though the <hi>Lambs</hi> and the <hi>Sheep</hi> make up the whole Church of Chriſt upon Earth; it cannot be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood, that the Church <hi>Oe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>umenical</hi> was here committed to the Charge of every, or of any one individual Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor; ſuch a Work being loaded with Moral Impoſſibility. But the Charge, being given perſonally and particularly, it muſt be underſtood of the Church <hi>Congregational;</hi> that is, that Part, or Congregation of the Church, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto every one is particularly, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Goſpel Order, called, and ſet as Paſtor, or Over ſeer. Thus you have the Charge it ſelf.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Here's the Argument, wherewith our Saviour enforces it; which is three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The <hi>Relations</hi> he hath to them: They are <hi>My</hi> Lambs, and <hi>My</hi> Sheep.
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:64639:10"/>Mine, whom you call your LORD, and your Maſter; yea, your Redeemer, and your Saviour: Therefore feed them for my ſake.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The <hi>Propriety</hi> he hath in them: They are <hi>Mine,</hi> and not <hi>Yours;</hi> the work of my hands, the Lot of my In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance, the Objects of my Care and Delight, the Price of my Blood, and the Fruit of the Travel of my Soul; for whoſe ſakes it is, that I have thus humbled my ſelf: Therefore take heed how you neglect the leaſt of them.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The other part of the Argument is concomitant to the Text; <hi>Loveſt thou me? q. d.</hi> If thou loveſt me, as thou profeſſeſt to do; ſhew thy Love to Me, in thy Care of Mine. Let my poor <hi>Lambs</hi> taſt the Fruits of my Love in thee. Let my <hi>Sheep</hi> be aſſur'd that thou loveſt Me, by thy Love to Them. It is like a careful and prudent Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band's paſſionate recommending the Care and Rule of his dear Children and Family, when about to leave them by Death; or a long Journey to his beloved Wife. If ever you had any
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:64639:11"/>Love for me; if theſe Children be mine, as I believe them to be, ſee that you carry your ſelf in all reſpects as becomes a diſcreet and loving Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent towards them: Take my Eſtate; fill up my room, and diſcharge the Offices of my Relation to them; and let them want nothing, for my ſake. This is that which is wont to be uſed as the laſt and moſt overcoming Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment amongſt deareſt Friends. If you love me, do ſo, or ſo: a kind of ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juring them by all the Bonds of Love and Friendſhip that are between them.</p>
               <p>And now, Sirs, you ſee, here's a Foundation for a much larger Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, than time or ſtrength will at preſent bear. I ſhall contract my ſelf into as narrow a Circle, as I am able, that I may not too far tranſgreſs the Bounds aſſigned me.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:64639:11"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CAP. II.</hi> The Doctrinal Propoſition Stated and Cleared.</head>
               <p>THIS practical Text appears to be very pregnant of practical Doctrine; which might be diſtributed into ſeveral Branches. But he that ſtudies brevity, muſt avoid all unneceſſary diviſion. I ſhall offer but theſe three.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>Propoſition I. <hi>That Believers are Chriſts own myſtical Flock, and He their great Shepherd.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Prop. II. <hi>That the Miniſters of the Goſpel are they, to whom the LORD Jeſus Chriſt hath committed the Care and Rule of this his myſtical Flock.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Prop. III. <hi>That a Miniſters want of Care and Concern for the Flock of Chriſt, is an indication of the want of Love to Chriſt himſelf.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:64639:12"/>
               <p>Either of theſe ſingly, would fill up more time than is allotted me for this Action. The ſecond <hi>Propoſition</hi> is that, wherein the ſtream of the <hi>Text</hi> ſeems to run; and unto which both the other will, without forcing, come in to its Improvement. Wherefore I ſhall lay down this for the <hi>Baſis</hi> and <hi>Bound</hi> of my following Diſcourſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That the Miniſters of the Goſpel are they, to whom the LORD Jeſus Chriſt hath committed the Care and Rule of his Myſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Flock.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the Proſecution of this Truth, I ſhall briefly anſwer theſe four Queſtions.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. What this <hi>Flock</hi> is, concerning which this charge is given, or, who they are, whom our LORD would have us to underſtand by <hi>His Lambs,</hi> and <hi>His Sheep?</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. Why theſe Names of <hi>Lambs,</hi> and <hi>Sheep</hi> are given them?</item>
                  <item>3. Who the <hi>Miniſters of the Goſpel</hi> are, with whom this charge is left?</item>
                  <item>4. What the <hi>Duty</hi> is that is required of them; or what our dear LORD
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:64639:12"/>and Maſter would have us to underſtand by Feeding them? And then ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude all with ſome uſeful Inferences, both to Miniſters and People.</item>
               </list>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> 1. <hi>What this Flock is, concerning which this Charge is given;</hi> or whom our LORD would have us to underſtand by <hi>His Lambs,</hi> and <hi>His Sheep?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sol.</hi> The Queſtion needs not many words. The general ſenſe of this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Scriptural Metaphor is obvious. But that which makes the queſtion, is that diſtinguiſhing (if it be here a diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhing) Relative <hi>My</hi> Sheep, <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.32, 33. We have there all the World divided into two ſorts, <hi>Sheep</hi> and <hi>Goats, i. e.</hi> Believers and Unbelievers. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore by <hi>Sheep,</hi> in that Scripture, and with whom the <hi>Lambs</hi> are alſo included, being oppos'd to the <hi>Goats,</hi> we may un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand no other than true Believers. The ſound and ſincere part of Profeſſors which is no larger than the Church In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſible. Theſe indeed are <hi>His Sheep</hi> in the moſt proper and peculiar ſenſe. But that the Word in the Text muſt not be
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:64639:13"/>ſo reſtrain'd, is certain; becauſe our Commiſſion would then be unintelligi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and loſe its ends; it being impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for us to be aſſur'd, who are the <hi>Sheep,</hi> and who the <hi>Goats,</hi> till the Judgment of the Great Day determine and reveal it. Who then are <hi>My Lambs,</hi> and <hi>My Sheep?</hi> If I may expound my Text by that of <hi>Matth.</hi> 28.19. the queſtion will well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nigh be anſwered. <hi>Go ye therefore, and teach all Nations.</hi> That <hi>Teaching</hi> here, is the ſame with <hi>Feeding</hi> in the Text, I ſuppoſe will be granted. <hi>All Nations, i. e.</hi> thoſe of all, and of any Nation, that are willing to receive the Goſpel, and to be taught by you. And that all Nations are <hi>His,</hi> both as Creator and Redeemer, I hope will not be denied. But then, how are <hi>all Nations</hi> call'd <hi>His Sheep,</hi> and <hi>His Lambs?</hi> I have already ſaid, that all Nations, are thoſe of the Nations, that would receive the Goſpel; of which ſort Chriſt hath had ſome in all Nations. Beſides, many of thoſe that are not actually his Sheep, are Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentially and Electively ſo. The ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent of the Commiſſion and Command ſeems to run thus. Feed all thoſe, both
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:64639:13"/>Young and Old, that will be fed by you; of what Nation, or Countrey, or Place ſoever they be; that thoſe that are not yet actually my Sheep, may be made ſo, and then cared and provided for as ſuch. This is the general Call of the Goſpel. <hi>If any man thirſt let him come unto me and drink,</hi> Joh. 7.37. <hi>And him that cometh to me I will in no wiſe caſt out,</hi> Joh. 6.37. All that will, may, and muſt be fed. But yet, not all alike. As there are <hi>Babes,</hi> and <hi>Strong Men</hi> in Gods Houſe; ſo there is <hi>Milk</hi> and <hi>ſtronger Meat,</hi> that which will cheriſh one, will choak ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. All Ordinances may not be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>differently adminiſtred unto all. In the Old Temple, there was the Inner and the Outer Court; ſo there is in the New. But this being a matter of Order and Diſcipline, may be recogniz'd in a more proper place. This little may now be enough to be ſaid on this firſt que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion.</p>
               <p>Queſt. 2. <hi>Why are theſe names of Lambs, and Sheep given them?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sol.</hi> We find 'tis a Metaphor, that
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:64639:14"/>the Spirit of God in Scripture delights much in. Were it expedient, 'twere eaſie enough to illuſtrate the Analogy in many particulars; But that it becomes not the preſent occaſion. I ſhall but ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt theſe two general Reaſons.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. To mind us what we are of our ſelves.</item>
                  <item>2. To teach us what we ſhould be.</item>
               </list>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>To mind us what we are of our ſelves.</hi> The <hi>Sheep,</hi> as one obſerves, is of all Cattel the moſt ſilly,<note place="margin">Franz. Hiſtor. Animal Sacr.</note> Fearful, Weak, and Unpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided for ſelf-defence; none ſo ſubject to Diſeaſes, and to be Infect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of one another. Nor any other Creature more apt to go aſtray, or ſo unapt to return, without the help and care of the Shepherd. No other kind of perfect <hi>Animal</hi> ſo unable to ſubſiſt, and to preſerve it's <hi>Species</hi> in the Earth, without the care and conduct of Man, as is the poor <hi>Sheep;</hi> therefore no other Metaphor more proper to expreſs the Nature and Condition of the Church of Chriſt in the World by; which with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:64639:14"/>the Wiſdom, Power, Providence, Faithfulneſs, Love, and All-ſufficiency of our Heavenly <hi>Shepherd,</hi> the LORD Jeſus Chriſt, muſt inevitably and eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally periſh.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>'Tis to teach us what we ſhould be.</hi> The <hi>Sheep,</hi> you know, is that Creature, which was of old, in a more eſpecial manner dedicated to God, and offered to him in Sacrifice; and made a Type of Chriſt, our great Propitiatory Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice. The firſt Offering to the LORD, that we find honour'd with his Accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, was that of <hi>Abel,</hi> of the <hi>Firſtlings of his Flock, Gen.</hi> 4.4. Beſides, the <hi>Sheep</hi> is a Creature, not only Ceremoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally clean, but is naturally cleanly, and delights not in the Mire and Dirt as the <hi>Sow.</hi> 'Tis a Meek, Innocent, Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient Creature, and us'd as a common Emblem of Patience. 'Tis one of the moſt profitable of Cattel; of which there is nothing, but is, one way or other, uſeful to all the purpoſes of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Life. And, which is very re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable, they have a natural Inſtinct of vehement Love and Regard for their
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:64639:15"/>own <hi>Shepherd;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Paſtores ſuos vehementer amant. Fr. ib.</note> as if they were Conſcious of their own weakneſs and need of him. The bare mention of theſe things being enough to direct the Spiritual Mind to their due application, I ſhall wave all manner of further en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>largement here.</p>
               <p>Queſt. 3. The Third Queſtion is this. <hi>Who the Miniſters of the Goſpel are, with whom this Charge of our dear Saviour is left?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sol.</hi> One would think, the Solution of ſuch a Queſtion as this, ſhould not be hard; nor is it ſo <hi>in Theſi,</hi> wherein the clear light both of Scripture and of Nature, is ſo concurring and convincing. And yet we find there is hardly any one thing, wherein Profeſſors (ſuch of them as are too apt to be led by the factious Principles of Ignorance and Prejudice) are more uncharitably diſagreed in, than in this. How miſerably the poor Church of Chriſt, by the malice and ſubtilties of the common Enemy, and the Carnality, Pride, and blind Paſſions of Profeſſors,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:64639:15"/>is torn into Rags of Diviſions and Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diviſions, is too well known, for me to inform you. And of all theſe, every Party is magnifying their own Teachers, as the only Miniſters of Chriſt; and ready to condemn all others as Hirelings, Falſe Teachers, Schiſmatical Intru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> This is a Lamentation, and let it be for a Lamentation. But could we return to a right Underſtanding of our plain rule in this Affair, how eaſily might the Caſe be brought to its due Iſſue? I know but theſe two things, that eſſentially denominate a Man to be a Miniſter of Jeſus Chriſt:</p>
               <p>Qualification, and Commiſſion.</p>
               <p>And neither of which is ſingly ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient. I am ſenſible, that I am now in a large Field, and in a ready way to be loſt in Controverſy; but that I have more practical and neceſſary work before me. Yet, I beſeech you, bear with me, while I explain my ſelf a little on theſe two heads; and I will be very ſhort, the Truth being commonly beſt ſeen in a few plain words.</p>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:64639:16"/>
               <p n="1">1. There muſt be <hi>Qualifications.</hi> But what? Of ſpecial, ſanctifying, ſaving Grace? This indeed is needful, and moſt deſireable, and morally conducive to the happy and glorious ends of the Miniſtry, both as to our ſelves, and thoſe that hear us; abſolutely neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry as the <hi>ſine quâ non,</hi> unto Salvation; but not ſo to Miniſterial Qualification. A man may be lawfully a Miniſter, that is not Spiritually a Member of Chriſt. The Sealed of the Tribe of <hi>Levi</hi> were but a Remnant, as of, any one of the other Tribes. Thoſe that in our Saviour's Time, ſate in <hi>Moſes</hi>'s Chair, were, for the moſt part of them, far enough from <hi>Moſes</hi>'s Spirit; and yet our Saviour owns them in their Office. <hi>Judas</hi> was a Diſciple, and ſent forth with a Commiſſion to Preach the Goſpel of the Kingdom, even by Him, who knew him to be inwardly a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil and a Traitor. But this is no new Doctrine, nor needs any proof to one that has not a mind to be contentious. But the <hi>Qualification</hi> here required, as abſolutely neceſſary, is <hi>Miniſterial.</hi> That whereby a Perſon is competently
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:64639:16"/>fitted for the diſcharge of all the work and duties of this ſacred Office, Ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doxy in Doctrine, ability and aptneſs in (at leaſt) the gift of Preaching and Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; skill and moderation in ruling, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And certainly there's a great difference between Miniſterial G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s and saving Grace. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> the particulars of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer you to <hi>Paul</hi>'s <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 1 <hi>Epiſt.</hi> ch. 3. and to <hi>Titus</hi> ch. 1.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>There muſt be Commiſſion. No man taketh this honour unto himſelf but he that is called of God, as was</hi> Aaron, <hi>Heb.</hi> 5.4. <hi>No man</hi> taketh <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> No man undertaketh, accepteth, or aſſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to himſelf, and of himſelf; that is, no man ought, or can without Sin, any way take, or receive <hi>this Honour,</hi> or uſurp this Office, <hi>but he that is called of God,</hi> that is delegated and commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioned by Gods Authority, and in the way of Gods appointment; tho' not in that immediate and extraordinary man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner as <hi>Aaron</hi> was, unleſs in like extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary caſes; yet by a Power and Diſpenſation, legally and orderly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:64639:17"/>from him, through ſuch Hands as he hath appointed and impower'd to this end. Qualification without Commiſſion makes not a Miniſter of Jeſus Chriſt; but ſuch a thing, as he calls a <hi>Thief</hi> and a <hi>Robber,</hi> a Sacrile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious <hi>Intruder;</hi> ſuch as were <hi>Corah</hi> and his Complices; and ſuch, as are too many in our days. And Commiſſion without Qualification, makes what the Prophet calls an <hi>Idol-ſhepherd,</hi> or <hi>Dumb-Dog,</hi> a <hi>Blind Guide.</hi> And who are they that have right authoritatively to exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine and judge of Qualification, or to conveigh Commiſſion to others, for the Conſervation of a Succeſſion in this ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Office, but thoſe that are themſelves both duely Qualified and Commiſſiona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted? And that too not ſingly, private<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, or arbitrarily; but according to the Rules given in this matter, by and from our ſupream LORD and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter Jeſus Chriſt in the New Teſtament. Methinks this ſhould not amount to a Queſtion, with any that have but read the Holy Scriptures, and own their Truth and Authority: or that have not abandon'd the conduct of common rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon;
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:64639:17"/>by whoſe light it is eaſie to ſee the equity and expediency of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture directions in this caſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> 4. We are now come to the laſt Queſtion. <hi>What the duty is, that is required of them? Or, What our dear LORD and Maſter would have us to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand by Feeding his Lambs, and his Sheep?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sol.</hi> The <hi>Flock,</hi> you ſee, is divided into two parts; the <hi>Lambs,</hi> and the <hi>Sheep.</hi> So is the Miniſterial Work that concerns them. <hi>Feed,</hi> and <hi>Rule,</hi> both which are equally, and inſeparably en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joined parts of this work, as appears in ſeveral very plain Scriptures, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.17. <hi>Let the Elders that rule well, be accounted worthy of double honour, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially they who labour,</hi> or they labouring, <hi>i. e.</hi> on the account of their labouring <hi>in Word and Doctrine,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. This is a Text that hath been ſufficiently vext by men of different Sentiments and Intereſts. I know no reaſon we have, from this Scripture, to infer two diſtinct. Orders
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:64639:18"/>of Ruling and Teaching Presbyters; ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing what is mention'd here, both of Rul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Labouring in Word and Doctrine, are but the eſſential and required Functi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of one and the ſame Sacred Order and Office; than which, I am not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned at preſent to look any further into any Truths, that are plainly enough ſtated in it, or any queſtions, that have been vainly enough ſtarted on it. And with which, there are ſeveral other Scriptures that agree in the ſame <hi>Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theſis,</hi> 1 Theſ. 5.12. <hi>We beſeech you Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, to know them which labour among you, and are over you in the LORD, and admoniſh you.</hi> Here are the ſame words applied to the ſame Perſons and Things, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>that are over you,</hi> or ſet and appointed over you <hi>in the</hi> LORD, <hi>i. e.</hi> according to the LORD, and in the things of the LORD, to rule in his Church; and who they are, but the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>thoſe that labour among you and admoniſh you?</hi> So <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.7. Thoſe that <hi>Rule</hi> are the ſame with thoſe that <hi>Preach the Word,</hi> and <hi>ver.</hi> 17. They are ſaid to <hi>Watch for Souls;</hi> which as it may imply other work, ſo
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:64639:18"/>it muſt import Preaching the Word; in which ſenſe the word is ordinarily uſed in Scripture: And here the <hi>Rulers</hi> and the <hi>Watch-men</hi> are the ſame. Many other Texts there are that freely offer to avouch this Truth; but theſe are enough to prove what I aim at: That the work of a Miniſter of Chriſt, is both to <hi>Teach,</hi> and to <hi>Govern</hi> the People committed to his charge. And he that is not fit to Govern, is not worthy to Teach them.</p>
               <p>But to obviate any ſcandalous Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flexions, that Ignorance or Envy may make on this Poſition, and Claim of our Governing Power in the Houſe of God, which is his Church: We hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily declare our Abhorrence of all thoſe Popith Tenets and Pretenſions, which are any way derogatory to the juſt Power and Authority of the Civil Government under which we live, and unto which we profeſs our chear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and conſtant Obedience, both as Men, and as Chriſtians. Our Spiritual Government of Gods Spiritual King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, in our reſpective Charges, being no more prejudicial to that of Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:64639:19"/>States and Kingdoms than is the Deſpotical, which is the Natural Right of every Family. Yea, ſo far from prejudicial, that it is accumulative, both of their Honour and Security; as the Experience both of the Primitive, and of the beſt Reformed Churches have unqueſtionably proved; and which might, in many particular inſtances (were it neceſſay) be demonſtrated. From what hath been now thus briefly ſaid, I conclude this Queſtion: That <hi>Feed my Lambs,</hi> and <hi>my Sheep,</hi> implies theſe two things, <hi>Teach them,</hi> and <hi>Rule them:</hi> wherein the whole works of the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſterial Office is included. But to tell you how they muſt be taught, and how they ought to be ruled, will need much more time than is here allotted me, or is now convenient for me to take. Yet this being the Main of my Errand to you, ſomething muſt be ſpoken to it, as time and ſtrength will ſerve, in the Applicatory part, to which I now proceed.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:64639:19"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CAP. III.</hi> The Doctrine improved by way of Inſtruction.</head>
               <p>THIS <hi>Doctrine</hi> would be uſeful, more ways than I ſhall be able now to apply it. Yet give me leave to ſuggeſt ſome of the more neceſſary things, under theſe three general Heads.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Inſtruction.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Exhortation.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Encouragement.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p n="1">1. By way of <hi>Inſtruction;</hi> and that in theſe eight particulars.</p>
               <p n="1">1. In the <hi>Right</hi> and <hi>Propriety,</hi> that Chriſt hath in his Church. They are his <hi>own Sheep, Joh.</hi> 10.3.4. No Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herd in the World ever had, or can have that abſolute, undefeaſible, ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream, independent, and natural Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priety in his Flock, as Chriſt hath in his. They are <hi>His,</hi> both <hi>as</hi> God, and
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:64639:20"/>as Redeemer. His by right of Creation, Donation, Purchaſe, Regeneration; and their own voluntary Choice and Self-dedication. His Portion, His Inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, His peculiar Treaſure. Nothing is nearer, nothing dearer to him than they. His Mark and his Name is upon them; his Spirit, his Nature, his Image, his Glory ſhines in them. The Scripture is full of his Claims to them; and by which they are diſtinguiſh'd and ſeparate from all the reſt of the World, <hi>Joh.</hi> 15.19. And this is the ground of that Caution. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.2, 3. <hi>Feed the Flock of God, which is among you—Neither as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Lords over God's Heritage.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Ruling, but not Domineering; Governing, but not Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannizing, <hi>more Regio imperantes;</hi> as De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puties and Rulers in truſt, not as Lords and Kings. <hi>Non Regnum, ſed Cura Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byteris commiſſa eſt;</hi> beccauſe they are not <hi>Yours,</hi> but <hi>God's</hi> Heritage, his <hi>Clergy;</hi> whether Miniſters or People; for the word, in the uſe, as well as derivation of it, reaches both. Church-Tyranny is an Encroachment upon Chriſt's pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar Right. To Rule with a Lordly
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:64639:20"/>Grandeur, with Rigour, or Arbitrari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, to Monopolize the Power, which ought to be more equally diſtributed, is very injurious, not only to the Flock, but to him, who is the LORD of it, and whoſe Servants and Stewards we profeſs our ſelves to be And, which is a guilt that the proudeſt <hi>He</hi> upon Earth will not have the hardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to own before his Judge another day.</p>
               <p n="2">2. In the tender <hi>Affection</hi> and <hi>Care</hi> he hath for them. Nothing is more apt to endear a thing to us, than <hi>Propriety.</hi> That which is our own, we love; though it be not as it ſhould be, nor as we wiſh, yet becauſe 'tis our own. And thoſe that do other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, are juſtly reckoned among the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>without natural Affection,</hi> and worſe than Infidels. But ſhould I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin to tell you, what dearneſs of Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection the LORD Jſus Chriſt hath for his poor little Flock, where ſhould I end? Eternity will be little enough, with admiration and praiſe to recount the glorious Soul-raviſhing Inſtances of this Love. He loved them ſo, as to
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:64639:21"/>leave the Eternal Throne of his Glory, and the ſweet Repoſe he had from Everlaſting in the Boſom of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, for them: So, as to humble and abaſe himſelf to the vile Raggs of our Humane Nature; to the Miſeries and Neceſſities of an indigent life; to the proud Scorns, and blaſphemous Indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities of a wicked, and horridly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grateful World; to the foul Tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and Buffettings of Satan; to the imputation of Sin, the only thing ſo abhorrent to his pure and ſinleſs Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; to the Bondage, Obedience and Curſe of the Law; to the Wrath of God, which he never in the leaſt, for himſelf deſerved; and which, to any one elſe, would have been utterly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſupportable; to the moſt ign<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>inious, torturous and accurſed Death of the Croſs; and to the power of Death, his own Servant and common Executio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, for a time. And all this his Love to them overcame, and ſweetned to him. Yea, and having loved them, he loves them ſtill, and will love them to the end, yea, without end. And therefore delights to ſpeak of them,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:64639:21"/>always with ſome Intimations of their dearneſs to him; as his Friends, his Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, his Children, his Lambs, his Spouſe, his Members, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> for all which I had no need to quote you the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. And as is his Love to them; ſo is his Care of, and Proviſion for them. When he ſaw it expedient for them to depart from them, as to his bodily preſence, and to leave them here in a Militant ſtate, expoſed to the Rage of his and their Enemies, both Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral and Infernal; to be hated, and tempted, and perſecuted to the death for his ſake; O how did his Soul pity them! with what compaſſion did he embrace them! and ſeal his unchange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Love to them! what a ſtream of endearing Affection and Care doth there run thro' his parting Diſcourſes with them! <hi>Joh.</hi> 14.15. and 16. How ſweetly doth he counſel and comfort them there! and is ſo concerned for them, that he ſeems to take no care for himſelf! though he knew that dreadful Hour was now come, wherein that Wrath muſt be poured out upon him, which none but the Omnipotent could
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:64639:22"/>ſtand under! And then how affectio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately doth he recommend them to his Father! <hi>Chap.</hi> 17. Leaves his written Word, his ſealing Ordinances, and his Ordained Miniſters, whom he ſtrictly charges with them; yea, gives his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Angels a charge concerning them; ſends his Holy Spirit, as a Sanctifier, and a Comforter to them; goes before, to prepare a Place for them; Negotiates all their Affairs, as a Faithful, Powerful and Prevalent Interceſſor with the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, in their Names and Nature; and aſſures them, that he will come again, and in due time receive them into the Eternal Poſſeſſion of his own Glory and Joy, with Himſelf and the Father in Heaven; and in the mean time will, in an inviſible manner, be with them alway, even unto the end of the Word! LORD! what is<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> Homo mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talis &amp; Miſer. Rad. ſecundum Euſeb. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liviſci.</note> 
                  <hi>Enoſh,</hi> wretched, worthleſs, guilty, ſin-ſinful <hi>Man,</hi> that ſo <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gets</hi> Thee, and deſerves to be for ever <hi>forgotten</hi> of thee, that thou art ſo very mindful of him?</p>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:64639:22"/>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>That the Miniſters of the Goſpel,</hi> i. e. Thoſe that are duly qualify'd, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioned, are the LORD's <hi>deputed Shepherds:</hi> They have both their ability and authority, originally and fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally from him, the only truly Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick, Infallible and Supream Shepherd, and Head of his Church. And in this ſenſe, we may without vanity ſay with the Apoſtle; <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.1. <hi>That we are the Miniſters, not of men, nor by man; but by Jeſus Chriſt, and God the Father, who raiſed him from the dead.</hi> We are appointed of him to be in his ſtead, to the Flock; and he hath promiſed to be with us, to direct us in, and to conduct us through both the Duties and the difficulties of our Work, to the end of the World.</p>
               <p>Suffer me now (my dear Brethren) to make a few ſhort Remarks on this Head, both for my own Admoniti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and yours.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Theſe only are Shepherds, that are duly qualify'd and call'd; <hi>I ſent them
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:64639:23"/>not, ſaith the Lord, yet they prophecy a lye in my name, that I might drive you out, and that ye might periſh, ye and the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets that prophecy unto you,</hi> Jer. 27.15. God never ſends a <hi>Meſſenger</hi> without his <hi>Errand:</hi> Whatever the <hi>Qualification</hi> ſeem to be, if the <hi>Call</hi> be not of God, be ſure there is a lye of one kind or other, in the Prophecy; for if God have no Errand in it, the Devil hath.</p>
               <p n="2">2. 'Tis no contradiction, nor Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſm in this caſe, for the ſame perſon to be both a <hi>Shepherd,</hi> and a <hi>Sheep;</hi> nay, nothing is more congruous. He that is a Captain had need to be a Souldier, yea, one of the beſt of Souldiers. Our great Shepherd is the Lamb of God, and his deputed Shepherds ſhould not be Goats, nor Wolves. For a man to be a <hi>Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er</hi> of others, and himſelf a <hi>Caſt away,</hi> What is there more ſhameful, or more dreadful.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Thoſe that are Shepherds but by deputation, be ſure muſt give an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count: The great Proprietor will not
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:64639:23"/>be defrauded: <hi>Of my hand, didſt thou re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire it, whether ſtolen by day, or ſtolen by night,</hi> Gen. 31 38. What miſcarries, through the Shepherds neglect, the Shepherd muſt account for: <hi>If thou doſt not ſpeak to warn the wicked from his way, that wicked man ſhall die in his iniquity, but his blood will I require at thy hand, Ezek,</hi> 33.8. And of the greater value the Flock is, the more ſevere will the account be.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Shepherds muſt <hi>cum Ovibus perno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctare, &amp; excubias agere;</hi> be the LORD's <hi>Watch-men:</hi> While the Shepherd is ſleeping, the Fox and the Wolf are waking and walking. O let not a night of ſecurity ſo ſoon eclipſe our dawning from the night of our late adverſity! Morning naps are ſweet, but in this caſe moſt dangerous. Our Enemy knows that we are apter to ſlumber in a calm, than in a ſtorm; and 'tis eaſy, though ſad to ſee what advantage he begins already to make of it. How can we forget what an Emphaſis our dear LORD hath ſet on that Word <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Watch therefore, Mat.</hi> 24.41.
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:64639:24"/>
                  <hi>Chap.</hi> 25.13. <hi>Chap.</hi> 26.41. <hi>Mark</hi> 13.35. and 37. <hi>Luke</hi> 21.36. <hi>&amp; alibi.</hi> On that miraculous Deliverance at the <hi>Read Sea</hi> it is ſaid, <hi>then believed they his words, they ſang his praiſe, they ſoon forgat his works, they waited not for his counſel,</hi> Pſal. 106.12, 13. Are not the Songs of our deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance yet in our mouths; and a deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance but begun, as was that of theirs? O let us not ſing our ſelves aſleep.</p>
               <p n="4">4. It informs us how neceſſary the Miniſtery of the Goſpel is. What becomes of a Flock without a Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herd? of a Family without a Steward? Of the Blind, without a Guide? Of the Infant, without a Nurſe? Of the Sick, without a Phyſician? Of an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my without an Officer? Of a City with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a Governor and a Watch man? In a worſe condition than any of theſe, is a Church, were it proper to call it a Church, without a Teacher and a Ruler. The Devil is aware of this, and very well knows where the ſtreſs of his Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt lies. If he can but effectually ſmite the Shepherd, the Sheep are his
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:64639:24"/>own; Therefore like the King of <hi>Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria,</hi> he commands his Captains and Legions, <hi>To fight neither with ſmall nor great, ſave only with the King of Iſrael,</hi> 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 22.31. And hence are all his Intrigues and Attempts by force and fraud, to diſgrace, diſcourage, divide, or corrupt, and any way to deſtroy the purity and the power, and were it poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible the being of the Miniſtry of the Goſpel in the World; Were it not for that promiſe, and that power and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs that hath, and will alway make it good, <hi>Matt.</hi> 16.18. <hi>The gates of hell ſhall not prevail.</hi> It might have been writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten long ago, on the univerſal ruins of God's <hi>Zion:</hi> THIS WAS ONCE THE CHURCH OF GOD. <hi>If it had not been the LORD who was on our ſide, now may Iſrael ſay Then they had ſwallowed us up quick,</hi> Pſal. 124. beg. But O how ſot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſhly unſenſible are the moſt of men, even of thoſe that are call'd Chriſtians; What a bleſſing and priviledge the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel Miniſtry is? yea, is it not a bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then with too many? <hi>Thou haſt been weary of me, O Iſrael, Iſa.</hi> 43.22. ſome on one account, and ſome on another,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:64639:25"/>are ready to look on the Miniſtry of the Goſpel, as an incumbrance, an unne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary charge, which might better be ſpar'd, and to ſay in their hearts, from the principles of <hi>Judas</hi>'s frugality; To what purpoſe is this waſte?</p>
               <p>Had I not many other things yet to ſpeak to how readily would my Pen run beyond the bounds aſſigned it, in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menting on the ineſtimable uſefulneſs of this glorious bleſſing of the Goſpel; and the ſhameful Atheiſtical, Heaven-tempting ingratitude of thoſe that are weary of it? O that a wanton, wrang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, ſelf-will'd, Goſpel-glutted Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, may not, after all that the God of patience hath done for us, provoke him to teſtify againſt us; that he is as weary of us, as we are of him!</p>
               <p n="5">5. It informs us, what an honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able work the work of the Goſpel is. 'Tis ſo both in its ſelf, and with relation to its Author, its Object, and its Ends: How contemptible ſoever it be in the eyes of ſome, and how unworthy and vile ſoever, ſome of thoſe are, that are admitted, or thruſt themſelves into it,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:64639:25"/>to the reproach of it. 'Tis not only a Work, but an Office, and an Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of the higheſt dignity; on the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of its Author, the LORD Jeſus Chriſt, who is exalted above all Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>palities and Powers, and hath a Name above every Name; The LORD of Lords, the King Eternal, Immortal, Inviſible, the only wiſe God; and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to whom every Knee ſhall bow; <hi>No man taketh this honour unto himſelf, but he that is called of God:</hi> 'Tis an Honour too great for any but God to beſtow; an Honour more immediately deriv'd from the Everlaſting Fountain of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, than any other <hi>Office</hi> in the World. On the account of its <hi>Object;</hi> the Myſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Flock, and ſpiritual Kingdom of Chriſt; the Noble Family and Houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold of God. Miniſters are Chriſt's Embaſſadors, not Pages nor Porters, though that were an honour, but his Embaſſadors and Repreſentatives, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.20. The <hi>Stewards</hi> of his Houſe, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.1. The <hi>Angels</hi> of the Churches, <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.20. He hath put his own Honour upon them, and hath told the Word, That what is done to them, he takes as
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:64639:26"/>done to himſelf; and hath required his Churches to honour them, for his, and for their Work ſake; <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Let them be accounted worthy, or let them be dignified with double honour. The honour of reſpect and maintenance is due to all that are faithful; but a double or greater degree of honour and authority to thoſe that are beſt qualify'd for, and moſt laborious in their Work. Where, by the way you may take notice, that Miniſters do not live, as perhaps ſome are ready to think, and to upbraid them too, on the Peoples Alms. Their maintenance is of God's allowance and precept; <hi>Non Eleemoſinae, ſed Honoraria;</hi> not <hi>Alms,</hi> but <hi>Rewards,</hi> by Divine Right due to them; I ſay, Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Right, <hi>in genere,</hi> though not <hi>in ſpecie.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But of this I would not now have once opened my lips but for your ſakes, who are the people, that no guilt of this kind may reſt on any of you, and that you may not have any unbecoming thoughts of us on this account.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, it is honourable too on the account of its ends; The converſion,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:64639:26"/>edification, and ſalvation of Immortal ſouls, The deſtroying the Works of the Devil in the World, and the pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling down his ſtrong holds, the repair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ruins of mankind by the Fall, and the reſtoring the Image of their Maker upon them, the negotiating the grand Affairs of a Peace between God and man, and of all the concerns of the Kingdom, of the Mediator upon Earth, the higheſt truſt that ever was committed to meer Creatures; The great Work and Deſign which the God of Heaven hath eſpouſed to glorify all his Attributes in, and which the Son of God was ſent into this lower World for. What are Earthly Kingdoms and Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions, and Intereſts to this? this is that ſwallows up all.</p>
               <p>Sirs, 'Tis not without regret that we ſhould be compell'd, as <hi>Paul</hi> once was, <hi>To magnify our Office, and to become fools in glorying,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor,</hi> 12.11. 'Tis an honour that we acknowledge our ſelves infinite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly unworthy of; yet it is the honour that our God hath put upon us, both for his own, and for your ſakes.</p>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:64639:27"/>
               <p n="6">6. It informs us what a Burthenſom Work the Miniſtry is. Burthenſom, not only in reſpect of the Labour of it; wherein if that faithfulneſs and dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence be uſed, as is neceſſary and requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, it is the heavieſt of all Employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in the World, and that which ſpends the ſtrength both of Body and Spirit more than any other. 'Tis true, there are too many that live idly, and work eaſily enough in this Laborious Calling, whoſe praiſe is not great in the Churches, and whoſe comfort is not like to abound in the day of ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count; but thoſe that love their Maſter, and their Work, and are duly ſenſible of their Charge, can find little time to be Idle.</p>
               <p>Alas, Sirs, what you ſee and hear of our Pulpit Work, is, or ſhould be the leaſt part of our Labour. Beſides, it is a burthenſom Work in reſpect of the many Temptations, Oppoſitions, and Diſcouragements that attend it; both from the World, the Fleſh, and the Devil. God knows, we are (the beſt of us) men, and but men ſubject to
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:64639:27"/>like Paſſions as others are; We that teach others, muſt teach our ſelves: We that carry the Light before you, have as much need of the Light as you. <hi>Not as though we had already attained, or were already perfect, Phil.</hi> 3.12. The boldeſt Officer is in himſelf no more ſhot-free than the Common Soldier, though his dangers may be greater. Pity us then, and pray for us, when you ſee a Temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation too ſtrong for us. We are more the Butt of the Dragon's Envy, and the Mark that his Rage aims at, than you, which makes our Poſt by ſo much the more difficult,</p>
               <p>Again, It is a burthenſom Work, in reſpect of the unſucceſsfulneſs of it; neither is this the leaſt part of our Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then. How very gladly would we ſpend, and be ſpent in the Service of our dear Flocks? We would not think the labour of our Brains, or Breaſts, our Studies, or Watchings; our Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vels, or Cares; our Reproaches, or Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings; no, nor our blood too much for them, could we but be comforted by them, with the good ſucceſs of all this: But when after all, our pains and adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:64639:28"/>and Prayers, and Tears, we ſee ſo little of the good Fruit we long for; ſo little Humility, ſo little Charity, ſo little Self-denyal, ſo little Mortification to the World; ſo little regular and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creet Zeal for God; this is that breaks our hearts, and makes us to walk hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vily.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, It is a burthenſom Work in reſpect of the conſequence of it, both to our hearers, and to our ſelves. To our hearers. Their Souls and Eternal Happineſs (and what have they dearer, what have they more?) is bound up in this burthen. To our ſelves. O the tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendous Charge, not only of our own, but of our Peoples ſouls, and the Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count that will ſhortly be required of us, when the time is come, that is at hand, that we may be no longer Stew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards! The ſerious conſideration of this is aſtoniſhing; O that it may now be awakning! Well might the Apoſtle cry out, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>; <hi>Who is ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent for theſe things?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:64639:28"/>
               <p n="7">7. It ſhews us the <hi>Sin and danger of intruders</hi> into this Office. 'Tis dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous both to themſelves, and to the Flock. To themſelves, in reſpect of their Uſurpation, which is highly Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legious, in reſpect of their Ends; which are wont to be baſe, vain-glorious, and ſelfiſh; and in reſpect of the Account, they muſt at laſt give for the blood of ſouls, which will be dreadful and dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning; dangerous to the Flock. The Thief cometh not but to ſteal, and to kill, to divide and ſcatter the Flock, and to ſerve his own Luſts on it, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever his flattering pretences may be. The Shepherd that comes not from God, and of God's ſending, tho in Sheeps Clothing, comes not to do God's, but his own and the Devils Work. I need not endeavour to prove that, which the diſmal Experience of the Churches hath in ſo many pernicious Inſtances, in all Ages more than ſufficiently proved; in whom Chriſt, and his Apoſtles Predi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions are fulfilled, <hi>Matt.</hi> 24.24. <hi>Acts</hi> 20.29, 30. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.1. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. begin. <hi>&amp;c. Whoſe judgment now of a long time
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:64639:29"/>lingereth not, and whoſe damnation ſlumbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth not.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I would not ſpeak this to the diſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement of any, whoſe hearts God hath ſtirred up to put their hands to the work of the Temple; but for the cauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of thoſe, who for baſe and low ends, or on wrong and miſtaken Principles, are ready to run when they were never ſent; tho the Tribe of <hi>Levy</hi> be numerous, and the Miniſtry, as well as many other Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſions among us, ſeems to be over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtock'd; yet have we ſtill need to pray the Lord of the Harveſt to ſend forth more Labourers into his Harveſt; ſuch as are both willing, and wiſe, and fitted for the Work of God, whereunto they are called; and then accordingly ſucceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in it.</p>
               <p n="8">8. Laſtly, It informs us of the <hi>Sin and danger</hi> of abuſing, oppoſing, ſlighting, or any way diſcouraging the leaſt of thoſe, whom Chriſt hath ſent and ſet to feed his Flock. To affront an Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor is all one as perſonally to affront him that ſent him. You know how dear, and doleful an Experiment <hi>Hanan</hi> and
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:64639:29"/>his people made of this, in the caſe of <hi>Dàvid</hi>'s Meſſengers, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 10. To a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe an Herald of War from a potent Enemy, is daring, and diſingenuous; but to deal injuriouſly with the Meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of Peace, is moſt provoking; none that hath power to do it, but will a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge ſuch a villany to the uttermoſt. This is the caſe; We are ſent by the Lord Jeſus Chriſt as the Ambaſſadors of Peace to the World, with the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry <hi>of reconciliation,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.18. Let them that now herein oppoſe, or malign us, ſee to it, how they will ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtify themſelves at that Barr, where they and we muſt ſhortly appear toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther indeed, as men, and as common Chriſtians: we neither deſerve, nor ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect any other than what is due to ſuch: But as we are the Miniſters of Chriſt, be aſſur'd that he very critically obſerves how we are treated; who they are that receive us; and who they are that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive us not: he obſerves not only how our Doctrine, but how our perſons are entertain'd; as every thing that is done for us, even to a Cup of cold Water: So every thing that is done, or ſaid, or
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:64639:30"/>contriv'd againſt us, is on record with him. You know what a caution he hath given; <hi>Touch not mine anointed, and do my Prophets no harm,</hi> Pſal. 105.15. <hi>He that toucheth you, toucheth the apple of his eye, Zech.</hi> 2.8. and what a <hi>Woe to the world</hi> he hath denounced, <hi>becauſe of offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,</hi> Matt. 18.7. To wrong us in our perſons, or perſonal concerns, will not be taken well by him: But to oppoſe or hinder us in that regular and faithful diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge of our Work and Office, and be reſented by him with a far greater indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation.</p>
               <p>Alas, Sirs, The trampling on us, as we are in our ſelves poor ſinful Worms, is hardly worth our complaining: what are we better than our fellow Mortals? But to trample on Chriſt in us; as we are not only his Children, but his Stew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards, and Ambaſſadors, and bear his Authority, is a guilt that will make the ſtouteſt and ſecureſt heart tremble, and cry to the Rocks and Mountains another day. Nor will the reproachful Names, of <hi>Schiſmaticks,</hi> or <hi>Separatiſts,</hi> wherewith they now ſalſely load us, juſtify them in that day.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:64639:30"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CAP. IV.</hi> The firſt part of the Paſtor's Charge, <hi>viz.</hi> To Feed the Flock.</head>
               <p>THE next <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> that I ſhall make of this Doctrine, ſhall be of <hi>Exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation;</hi> which I ſhall direct
<list>
                     <item>1. To Paſtors.</item>
                     <item>2. To People.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>To Paſtors.</hi> Reverend! and Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved! Gods Providence, and your Call having laid this duty upon me, the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthieſt and unfitteſt of all my Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren; I dare not but be faithful, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to my meaſure, both to my ſelf, and to you: as my own Monitor, and your Remembrancer.</p>
               <p>Are we indeed ſome of thoſe, to whom the Charge of <hi>Feeding</hi> and <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verning</hi> the Flock of Chriſt, both his Lambs, and his Sheep, is committed? O let us then <hi>take heed to the Miniſtry,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:64639:31"/>which we have received in the LORD, that we fulfil it.</hi> You know whoſe Admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition this was, and to whom, it was ſent, <hi>Col.</hi> 4.17. Nor need I tell you, that it as much concerns us, as ever it did <hi>Archippus.</hi> The Miniſtry which we have received <hi>in the</hi> LORD. In the Name, and by the Authority, and in the Houſe of the LORD; and the concerns of his Houſe. Or <hi>from the LORD,</hi> and <hi>for the LORD: that we ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fil it;</hi> diſcharge every part of it with fulneſs of diligence, fidelity, and care, to the utmoſt of our Underſtanding and Power, with all impartiality, aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duity, and perſeverance to the end. But this is yet too general. The <hi>Object</hi> of our Charge, you ſee, is double. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, The <hi>Lambs,</hi> and the <hi>Sheep,</hi> and ſo is the <hi>Act</hi> double; <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Feed</hi> and <hi>Rule,</hi> as was before expounded.</p>
               <p>I ſhall firſt conſider the <hi>Object,</hi> and then ſute my Exhortation according to the <hi>Act</hi> that reſpectively concerns it. And,</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>The Lambs.</hi> The younger ſort,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:64639:31"/>both in reſpect of Age, and in reſpect of Grace. Here I would fain ſpend ſome time; but conſidering to whom I am ſpeaking, I can the more content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly contract my ſelf. Sirs! you ſee, our LORD will not have theſe neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected; but hath given them firſt in his Charge to us. <hi>Feed my Lambs.</hi> Every wiſe Shepherd is wont to be very fond of his Lambs, and knows 'tis his Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt ſo to be, and ſhould not we? Our LORD himſelf the Great Shepherd, gathers them with his Arm, and carries them in his Boſom, and ſhould not we do ſo? He ſhew'd a peculiar delight he had in Little Ones, while he was here in the Fleſh, <hi>Mat.</hi> 19.13, 14. <hi>Mar.</hi> 10. 13, 14. <hi>Luk.</hi> 18.15, 16. <hi>ch.</hi> 9.47, 48. <hi>Mat.</hi> 21.16. And ſhould not we be here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, like our LORD and Maſter?</p>
               <p n="1">1. Then, let us take them as one ſpecial, I had almoſt ſaid, the only hopeful part of our Charge; I mean, as to converting work, and put them into our daily Prayers and Interceſſions at the Throne of Grace, if ſo be there may be hope in our End, and the next
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:64639:32"/>Generation may be better than their Fathers have been. There are ſome, who are Ignorantly enough influenced by Anabaptiſtical Principles, that will hardly allow the <hi>Lambs,</hi> in this ſenſe, to be any part of our Charge. I ſhall not meddle with that Bone of Conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tìon now, and hope there are no <hi>Deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rìums</hi> of this kind in any of our Brains. Tho' thoſe that are under their firſt Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>victions, and are young in the Faith, may, improperly, be called <hi>Lambs,</hi> yet theſe are they, who, in Scripture Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, are ſaid to be <hi>with Young,</hi> and are plainly diſtinguiſhed from <hi>the Lambs,</hi> Iſa. 40.11. 'Tis ſtrange that any, but the Devil, ſhould quarrel at this part of our Work.</p>
               <p n="2">2. As part of our Charge, let us take all proper and rational Methods, that lye within our reach, and their capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city, to teach and inſtruct them in all the neceſſary points of the Chriſtian Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, both Doctrinal and Practical. This was the Command of God by <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> and the conſtant practice of the Conſcientious in that Church. And
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:64639:32"/>herein the firſt and pureſt, the beſt ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tled and moſt thriving Churches of the Gentiles have been exemplarily diligent, and eminently ſucceſsful; nor was there ever any Age more plentifully furniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with ſuch helps, and plain Catechiſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Syſtems of ſound words to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, than is the Age we live in, which, if diligently and duely improv'd, may yet ſave us a Remnant, and be as a <hi>Nail given us in his Holy Place:</hi> a happy pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage of a work of Reformation, if not in this, yet in the next Generation. But here theſe five words of caution may be neceſſary.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That their memories be ſo im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy'd, as not to be over burden'd, a due regard being had to that inſupera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble difference, which Nature hath made in the diſtribution of this Faculty. Tho' ſloth or dullneſs ought not to excuſe, yet the burden ſhould not be made too heavy. We muſt drive as <hi>Jacob</hi> did, <hi>Gen.</hi> 33.13. as the weak and tender of the Flock can bear. Prudence muſt be applied here.</p>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:64639:33"/>
               <p n="2">2. That they do not reſt in the bare exerciſe of Memory, as Children are exceeding apt to do; but that our beſt endeavours to be uſed, to conveigh the Notions of Divine Truths, as they are capable, into their Underſtandings, which will be no little help and advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage to a weak Memory. And herein ſhould our skill and condeſcenſion ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear in plainneſs and familiarity of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion; yet with that ſeriouſneſs, ſweetneſs, and gravity, as doth become our Perſons and Office. And in order hereto, an account ſhould be taken of them, by ſuch other eaſie queſtions, as are not formally learnt, but plainly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded in, and may readily be anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by what is ſo learnt, for the trial and exerciſe of their Intellectuals. Of which kind alſo we have made ready to our hands, the uſeful labours of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, who have travell'd in this Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince, on that excellent <hi>Compendium</hi> of Theology, compos'd by the Reverend Aſſembly of Divines at <hi>WEST MIN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>STER:</hi> and which hath deſervedly obtain'd the general acceptance of all the Orthodox in the Proteſtant Churches.</p>
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:64639:33"/>
               <p n="3">3. Becauſe we know, that the Devil will be Catechizing the Heart, in theſe Young Ones, while we are Cathechiz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Ear, and the common Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding; and will be digging his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termines againſt us, in the hidden parts of the Soul, and doubling his Fortifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions on the Ground of a depraved Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; we ſhould endeavour, with all our Holy Art, to make them ſenſible of their particular and real concern in theſe things of God, and of their Souls; ſo that their Conſciences may be awaken'd and rouz'd, and the happy Foundations of a ſerious, as well as early Religion be laid in them. And perhaps we may find greater ſucceſs herein than we are aware of, or are apt to hope for. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience is as natural to them as Reaſon, and ſhould be nouriſh'd up with it, and as we find in all other things, the young<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, the more tender, and eaſie to be wrought upon. Tho' Fear be ſaid, by the Atheiſtical Philoſopher, to be that which firſt made, that it (in their ſenſe) fancied and imagined, God, in the World; yet were it not for this Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natural Principle of Conſcience, Fear
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:64639:34"/>would not make that clear and abiding Impreſſion on the Rational Nature, as it doth. Unleſs we manage our work with them ſo, as is proper to effect the grand Deſign of their Converſion, we do nothing to any good purpoſe; but loſe our propereſt and moſt acceptable time of doing their Souls that good, for which they may bleſs God for us in the upper World.</p>
               <p n="4">4. We ſhould reſt with them, in the Doctrinal, or Theoretical part; but eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially inſiſt on the Practicals of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion; and with ſuch plain and ſuitable applications, as are more obvious to their weak Underſtandings; that ſo they may come to perceive the end and uſe of their Inſtruction and Knowledge, and a Harmony may be form'd in them betimes, <hi>&amp; abovo,</hi> between their Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples and their Practices Which is the moſt hopeful way to obviate that common Cavil of the World againſt Early Piety, grown into a Proverb, <hi>A young Saint, and an old Hypocrite.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. Our Carriage towards them, and
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:64639:34"/>Care for them ſhould in all reſpects be ſuch, as may engage their Affections; which are naturally more early and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily exerted, than acts of Judgment and Underſtanding; that they may, as ſoon as poſſible, come to taſte the ſweetneſs of the ways of God. By ſuch an advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage as this, you know, it is, that our E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy, the Devil, is wont to be before<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand with us; by inflaming the ſenſual Appetite, and engaging the Affections, and corrupting the Will with the car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal pleaſures of Sin, and the Luſts of the Fleſh, before the Judgment is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightned, or the Conſcience awaken'd to diſcern, and to reſiſt the Temptations, wherewith he is too hard for them. Herein then it is good policy to prevent him. When we have gotten the Hearts of our Little Ones, with what pleaſure, and zeal, and innocent emulation will they go on in their work, which will make it much the eaſier both to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and to us. I could enlargehere; but that I know to whom I am ſpeaking, <hi>Verbum ſatis ſapientibus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. The other part of our Charge are
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:64639:35"/>the <hi>Sheep;</hi> and here, as I have ſaid, is double work. Theſe muſt both be <hi>Fed,</hi> and <hi>Rul'd.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. They muſt be <hi>Fed.</hi> 'Tis my com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, that I am now ſpeaking to ſuch, as God hath made both able and apt ſo to do; and who, I hope, have no need of my <hi>Directions</hi> in it, or <hi>Spurs</hi> to it. Wherefore I ſhall only hint at ſome few more general heads of the things you much better underſtand than my ſelf.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>They muſt be fed with wholeſome Food; The ſincere Milk of the Word,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, ſound, pure, and inadulterated Doctrine, Divine and Scripture Truths; the Bread of Life, of Heavens preparing; and not the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of our own Hearts. Unwhole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome Food breeds Diſeaſes, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ends in Death. The Shepherd were as good ſtarve his Flock, as poiſon it. O how dangerous then is blindneſs, or giddineſs, or ſelf-will in a Spiritual Guide! What need have we with un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prejudiced minds, to ſtudy the Holy
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:64639:35"/>Scriptures, to take heed of raſhneſs, or ſingularity in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>otions that we eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pouſe? To Watch and Pray for that Spirit of Truth, which is promiſed us of God to guide us into all Truth, that we do not gather <hi>wild Gourds,</hi> inſtead of wholeſome Herbs for the <hi>Pot?</hi> Miſtakes in matters of Doctrine, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Life of Souls is concerned, are of very evil conſequence.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>They muſt be fed with plain Food.</hi> The plaineſt food, ſo that it be whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, clean and duely prepar'd, is the moſt healthy and nouriſhing. The true Subſtantial Houſhold-bread is fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt for the Houſhold of God. Not Airy Notions, nor doubtful Queſtions of Polemical, or State Divinity, which foment Factions and vain janglings, and fill our Auditors with Wind and Aſhes. How jealous was the Apoſtle of the Churches which he had planted in the plainneſs and ſimplicity of the Goſpel, <hi>leſt any ſhould ſpoil them thro' Philoſophy? Col.</hi> 2.8. The Churches of Chriſt have been but little beholden to <hi>School Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity,</hi> which hath proved but as a <hi>Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:64639:36"/>of Linnen and Woollen,</hi> or as an <hi>Ox and an Aſs</hi> in Gods Plough. Alas! my Brethren, our poor Auditors, for the moſt part of them, can't digeſt theſe quaint Terms and critical diſtinctions; they are Husks and Stones to them, and not Bread; that which may nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, or at leaſt pleaſe us, will choak them; what may be Orthodox in it ſelf, and in our ſublimer ſenſe, may be Heterodox, and worſe to them, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they can't reach it: and this may be one reaſon among others, why our LORD choſe not his Apoſtles out of the Schools of the Learned, but from among the Fiſher Boats and poor Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chanicks; that the ſimplicity of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel might not be loſt in the Airy Clouds of vain Philoſophy. Neither doth the affected curioſity of flo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>id, enticing words of man's Wiſdom, become our Sacred Function. Theſe are things too carnal, to be bleſt with the demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Spirit, and of Power. 'Tis true, a genuine elegance of Speech, and readineſs of utterance is a gift, that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves not to be deſpiſed, but the more it is, or ſeems to be affected, or ſtudied,
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:64639:36"/>the more it looks like a vain Pomp of Words, and loſes both its value and efficacy.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Their Food muſt be ſuitable and ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable;</hi> elſe it will breed a <hi>Nauſeam,</hi> flatulent Crudities. and Surfeits. Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in is ſeen very much of the <hi>Wiſdom</hi> and <hi>Faithfulneſs of a Steward, to give to the Houſhold, their meat in due ſeaſon, Mat.</hi> 24.45. With what ſtrength of Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment doth <hi>Paul</hi> cloath this advice of his to <hi>Timothy,</hi> 2 Tim. 2.15. <hi>Study to ſhew thy ſelf approved unto God, a Workman that needeth not to be aſhamed, rightly dividing the word of Truth,</hi> aptly and ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonably applying to every one his Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. A word fitly ſpoken, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>ſuper rotis ſuis, rotunde, rempeſtive, &amp; quibus modis dici debet,</hi> with the prudent obſervation of preſent circumſtances, <hi>is like Apples of Gold in Pictures of Silver.</hi> Nothing can be more lovely, or accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table. This is ſpoken of Chriſt, as one eminent part of the glory and excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of his Goſpel Miniſtry, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 50.4. <hi>The LORD GOD hath given me the Tongue of the learned, that I know how to ſpeak a word in Seaſon to him that is weak.</hi> A healing word to the broken in Heart;
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:64639:37"/>a word of Inſtruction to the Ingnorant; of Conviction to the Secure; of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futation to Seducers; of Reduction and Confirmation to the Seduced, and Weak; and of Terrour to the Obſtinate and Impenitent, and to all theſe, ſo ſeaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably, ſuitably, and prudently, that it may not be the caſting of Pearl before Swine. To this end a Paſtor muſt ſtudy Men and Things, as well as Books and Notions. Muſt know, and obſerve, and ſute him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to the ſtate of his Flock; and the particular tempers of thoſe whom he hath to do. <hi>Of ſome have compaſſion, mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a difference. And others ſave with fear, pulling them out of the fire, hating even the Garments ſpotted by the Fleſh, Jud.</hi> 22.23. What will heal one, will but ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſperate another; and what will inflame one will but awaken another; and what will be hearkened to at one time, will be rejected at another. Herein is need of your Wiſdom, Fidelity, Patience, and indefatigable Induſtry.</p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>Their Food muſt be gently cleanſing and healing;</hi> like the Leaves of the <hi>Tree of Life, which were for the healing of the Nations; Rev.</hi> 22.2. The LORD
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:64639:37"/>knows, the Flock is feeble and ſickly; daily liable to a thouſand diſeaſes and diſaſters. When-ever we walk among them, we hear their complaints; or, which is worſe, we ſee, to our grief, the evident ſymptoms of the foul and dangerous diſeaſes they lye under, and hardly ſenſe enough to complain. Their Food muſt be Medicinal, as well as Nouriſhing. We had need to be Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicians, as well as Shepherds: Yea, all the Shepherds of Chriſt's ſending are ſo. Men will not commit the Care of their Flocks to ſuch, as can only drive them, and fleece them; but to ſuch as underſtand what is healthy and beſt for them, and what their common Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ladies are, and how to cure them: And is not Chriſt as tender of his Flock, as Men are of theirs? See <hi>Ezek.</hi> 34. <hi>per totum.</hi> There you may read what God ſays in this caſe, both of his Shepherds, and of his Sheep: <hi>The diſeaſed have ye not ſtrengthened, neither have ye healed that which was ſick, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther have ye bound up that which was broken—but with force and with cruelty have ye ruled them;</hi> v. 4. <hi>Therefore I am
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:64639:38"/>againſt the Shepherds; and I will require my Flock at their hand, and cauſe them to ceaſe from feeding the Flock;</hi> v. 10. O my Brethren! the Charge of our LORD's Flock is tremendouſly great and weighty: Immortal Souls are of an ineſtimable value. And if we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the preſent State of the Churches; the lamentable Breaches, and Spiritual Diſeaſes of all kinds, that are upon them, and the great Diſpleaſure that is ſignified from Heaven againſt them; how can it but kindle our Compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, and quicken our Zeal, not only to bewail the hurt of the Daughter of <hi>Zion;</hi> but to apply all thoſe proper Remedies, that lye within our reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive capacities; and humbly to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plore the Divine Aſſiſtance, to make all our Medicines and Methods ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful? But in dangerous and complicated Caſes, how wary and very watchful muſt that Phyſician be, that makes Conſcience of ſhedding Blood! Heal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing without cleanſing, will but make them the more rotten; and cleanſing without healing, will exaſperate the ill humours, and caſt them out of one Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:64639:38"/>into another, and perhaps worſe. But I deſign not, and hope I need not to multiply words to you, my Brethren, who are fitter to give, than to receive Advice in this caſe, from ſuch a one as I. And all this muſt be done;</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Impartially;</hi> both as to Perſons and Things. An allowed partiality is inconſiſtent with ſincerity; and as great a ſtubling block, in ſome caſes, as we can lay before the feet of thoſe, that are apt to ſtumble. I know 'tis hard to Fleſh and Blood, to walk upright on ſo uneven a ground as we have, now a long time, been treading; and cannot but dolefully reſent the Temptations that too many are expoſed to, thro' the hard circumſtances of their conditions in the World. Though all that looks like partiality, be not ſo; Prudence di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recting, and that with warrant from Scripture, <hi>to make a difference,</hi> and not to uſe the ſame Meaſures with one, as with another; yet the ſelfiſh Spirit of Envy, Cenſoriouſneſs and Ignorance, that is in the World, is always ready to take offence, where there is none
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:64639:39"/>given. It concerns us therefore, that with holy watchfulneſs and unbyaſſed reſolution, abandoning all baſe Reſpects, and private Intereſts, we ſo comport our ſelves in all caſes, and towards all perſons, as that our hearts may have no cauſe to reproach us ſo long as we live.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Experimentally and Practically. Thou that teacheſt another, teacheſt thou not thy ſelf?</hi> Our Sermons, in their moſt preſſing and practical Appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations, ſhould be firſt, and eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially Preacht to our own hearts; that from the heart, they may warmly reach the hearts of our Hearers. Like good Nurſes; we ſhould firſt taſte and chew the Meats that we feed our Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren with. 'Tis ſhameful and dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, for one that is called a Miniſter of Chriſt, to be able to ſpeak of Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual things only by hear-ſay, or by Books. <hi>Every Scribe which is inſtruct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed unto the Kingdom of Heaven, is like unto a man that is an houſholder, which bringeth forth out of his Treaſure things new and old, Matth.</hi> 13.52. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>the good Treaſure,</hi> or Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſury
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:64639:39"/>
                  <hi>of the heart;</hi> as <hi>cap.</hi> 12.35. A Jewel in the head, and Poiſon in the heart, is worſe than a Toad in God's Eye. <hi>Turpe eſt doctori, &amp;c.</hi> The Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of Chriſt muſt be <hi>Enſamples to the Flock,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.3. And wherein? <hi>In Word, in Converſation, in Charity, in Spirit, in Faith, in Purity,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.12. Their Lives muſt teach, as well as their Lips. They muſt Lead, as well as give the Word of Command; that they may be able to ſay, <hi>Be ye followers of us, as we are alſo of Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Prudently.</hi> The imprudent manage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of a Truſt, is one way of betray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it. Thoſe that live in a Subtil and Serpentine Age, had need to be wiſe as Serpents. <hi>Who then is a faithful and wiſe Servant?</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Matth.</hi> 24.45. Where theſe Qualifications are well met, they make the happieſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction in the Heavens of the Church. A Man may be learned, and yet not prudent; witty, and yet not wiſe; honeſt, and yet not diſcreet; good Scholars, and yet no good Pilots; zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, but not according to knowledge.
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:64639:40"/>'Tis pity that Chriſtian Prudence ſhould be abuſed; that ſo noble and generous a Virtue ſhould be enſlav'd, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate into Vice; or that which is ſo eminently uſeful, and abſolutely neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary, ſhould get an ill name. But tho' it do indeed too often deſerve to be ſo cenſured; yet it is apparent enough, that thoſe that have the leaſt ſhare of it, are the moſt forward, and the moſt unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable in their uncharitable Cenſures. 'Tis as natural and common for the weak (who are worſt able, and have leaſt reaſon) to <hi>Judge;</hi> as it is for the ſtrong, to <hi>Deſpiſe.</hi> It concerns us then to be very wary that we ſteer aright between the two Extreams in this caſe. Let our Prudence be founded in an holy Integrity, and exerciſed with due re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard to the Rules of Charity; and then we need not value the Cenſures of Men, nor fear any juſt Cenſures of Conſcience.</p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>Diligently.</hi> An Office of great Truſt and Importance, requires great diligence. Where there are many Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, there muſt be the more watching.
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:64639:40"/>No Office in the World is of like im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance to this Are Princes God's Vicegerents upon Earth; the Repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatives and Upholders of his Authority amongſt Men? It is but <hi>in Temporalibus, &amp; circa Sacra.</hi> The Faithful Miniſters of Chriſt are his Ambaſſadors, repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent his Perſon, and execute his Office, in the concerns of an higher nature. Better there were neither Princes, nor People, nor Sun, nor Moon, nor Stars, nor Viſible Heavens, nor Earth, than that there ſhould be no Goſpel Preacht to fallen Man; no way of Salvation opened by and thro' a Saviour; and no Means diſcovered of eſcaping the Miſeries, and obtaining the Happineſs of that Eternal State in the next Life. Better no Temporal Kingdom of Men, than no Spiritual Kingdom of Chriſt in the World. Nor is there any other Office, or Intereſt in the World that hath ſuch, and ſo many Enemies. That Spirit of Malignity which was breathed from Hell, thro' that crooked Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent in Paradiſe, hath leavened the whole Maſs of Mankind, and is ſtill working in the Children of Diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:64639:41"/>The Dragon and his Angels are engaged in this War; Enemies that never ſlumber nor ſleep; that never tire, nor deſert. The Earth is full, and the Air is full; yea not only the Heathen World, but the Church it ſelf is full of theſe Enemies. And more ways they have to make their Aſſaults, and to proſecute their Deſtructive Counſels, viſibly and inviſibly, by force and by fraud, than it is eaſie to enume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, or to diſcover. And alas! what are we in oppoſition to ſuch an Enemy, but as <hi>Iſrael</hi> before the <hi>Syrians, like two little Flocks of Kids, but the Syrians filled the Countrey?</hi> 1 <hi>King.</hi> 20.27. How ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ways might I eaſily enlarge on the greatneſs of this Importance? But I will not pretend to inſtruct my In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructers. Where the Enemies are mighty, and many, and vigilant, the ſtrength, or ſtratagems to oppoſe them ſmall, the time ſhort, the conſequence everlaſting, and the loſs irrepairable, there is need of Diligence.</p>
               <p n="5">5. <hi>Couragiouſly.</hi> The Miniſtry is a Warfare; a Service of hardſhips and
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:64639:41"/>hazards. Courage becomes a <hi>Souldier;</hi> much more an <hi>Officer.</hi> The Coward is not far from a Traitor. They are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly principl'd alike, and there is but the odds of a Temptation between the one and the other. Courage is the Life of a Souldier, and one of the ſureſt Pledges of Victory. When God ſent forth his Servant <hi>Joſhua,</hi> and gave him a Commiſſion to lead his People over <hi>Jordan,</hi> to their promiſed Poſſeſſion; though he had aſſured him of his ſpecial Preſence with him; yet knowing what is in the heart of the beſt of Men, he ſaw it needful to inculcate this Charge on him, no leſs than three times in one ſhort Speech; <hi>Joſh.</hi> 1.6. <hi>Be ſtrong and of a good Courage. Only be thou ſtrong and very couragious.</hi> Verſ. 7. <hi>Have not I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded thee? Be ſtrong, and of a good Courage; be not afraid,</hi> Verſ. 9.</p>
               <p>This may ſerve to caution us, both of giving way to our own fears; and of preſuming on our own ſtrength. Bold <hi>Peter</hi> was as eaſily overcome, as one of a more daſtardly ſpirit could have been. My Dear Brethren! I know I need not read you a Lecture
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:64639:42"/>of Chriſtians Courage. You have ſeen the high and terrible hand, wherewith our God hath led us theſe thirty years, thro' many Temptations and Tryals of Affliction, that have befallen us in this Wilderneſs: We will not ſpit on God's Rod now, nor aggravate our paſt Sufferings to the reproach of the guiltieſt of Inſtruments; but will here ſet up to the LORD, our <hi>Eben-ezer,</hi> who hath hitherto helped us. And from the times that have paſſed over us, let us receive inſtruction for what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever doth yet abide us. 'Tis neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary that our Faith and Patience have <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, their <hi>perfect work,</hi> their per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecting and crowning work: O let not the preſent <hi>Calm</hi> effeminate our Courage, nor tranſport it to any wrath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Indecencies; but let us preſs on, with our Loyns always girt in the way of our duty, if the will of God be ſo, prepared with an unſhaken reſolution for hotter Services, and ſorer Tryals, than yet we have been called unto.</p>
               <p n="6">6. <hi>Compaſſionately.</hi> O Sirs! what Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject is there in the World, that ſo cries
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:64639:42"/>for our pity and help, as the wretched Soul that is periſhing by his own hands? That is ready to ſtarve, and die eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally for want of Bread? That is blind, and running on ignorantly, and preſumptuouſly on everlaſting deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and ſporting with his own dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation? That is caught in the ſnares of the Devil, and cannot eſcape? Or, that is held on the torturing Rack of a ſelf-condemning Conſcience? That is plung'd in the amazing Horrours of Deſpair, and would give all the World for one glimpſe of hope, whoſe groans and complaints are able to break an heart of Flint? And is it not with ſuch as theſe that we have to do? Are not the moſt of Men in one or other of theſe Extreams? either ſenſleſs, or raving? too confident, or too diffident? Are not ſuch as theſe to be pitied? How can our bowels but be in pain for them? Have we our ſelves had the experience of ſuch a caſe, and can we make light of it? Yea, the Relation wherein we ſtand towards them, calls for our compaſſion, as we are their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, their Nurſes, their Shepherds,
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:64639:43"/>their Phyſicians. And what a pattern of Compaſſion have we in our deareſt LORD and Maſter! wherein it is our Duty and Glory to imitate him, as <hi>Paul</hi> did, <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.8. <hi>For God is my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord, how greatly I long after you all in the bowels of Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> The leſs of Compaſſion, the more like the Devil.</p>
               <p n="7">7. <hi>Patiently.</hi> We are hence called of God, as Souldiers, to militate in the Kingdom and Patience of Jeſus Chriſt; and we muſt expect to endure hardneſs, as our LORD, for our ſakes, and for our Example hath done before us, No ſort of Men in the World have more need of Patience, than we; and that not only with relation to them with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out; but to them within. From thoſe without; what ſcorn and contempt, what ſlanders and reproaches, what en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy and oppoſition, what plottings and perſecutions, and railing and rage muſt we look for? How hard and how long muſt we labour to recover one dead Soul to life? What difficulties muſt we break thro' to reſcue one poor Sheep out of the Dens of the Thieves, or of
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:64639:43"/>the Beaſts of Prey? O what need have we of Patience, to deal with blind, proud, graceleſs, hardened Sinners! Would we give the World the <hi>Jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals</hi> of our Warfare; we might pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce a Piece of the ſame kind with that of the Apoſtle; 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.23, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But beſides thoſe things that are with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out, that which cometh unto us daily, the Care of the Churches committed of God to us: How many weak ones? how many froward, paſſionate, ſelfiſh, luke-warm and diſorderly ones have we to exerciſe our Patience with? When God's time was come, according to his Promiſe, to lead that froward, murmu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, unſtable People out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> he choſe one of the meekeſt and patienteſt Men then upon Earth to do it, <hi>Numb.</hi> 12.3. Is not this one of the moſt glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious and uſeful Pieces of our Spiritual Panoply, both as Chriſtians, and as Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters? Which is given us in particular Charge? 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.11. <hi>Titus</hi> 2.2. And which we ſhould keep bright by daily exerciſe? O what ſad work ſhall we make, if Impatience once get the Reins of us? And hath not long Experience to
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:64639:44"/>our ſorrow tought us, that whatever the provocations be, fretting, and ſtorming, and paſſionate youthful heats, or caprici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous repartees, are a poor kind of revenge, and as unſucceſsful, as it is an irrational way to help it. A man's prevailing Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion is his weakneſs; which, if one have charity for himſelf, he will be careful to ſuppreſs and conceal: much leſs ſhould he, that is a Teacher of others, defile the Pulpit with the proclamation of it.</p>
               <p n="8">8. Laſtly, <hi>Perſeveringly.</hi> He that hath put his hand to God's Plow, muſt not look back. Tho the work be hard and painful, the difficulties great, the diſcouragements many; yet we muſt hold up, and hold on, and hold out, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that we ſhall reap in due ſeaſon, if we faint not. We, unto whom this ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Office is, according to Scripture Order committed, have our Ears bored to the Poſts of God's Sanctuary, for ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, <hi>durante vitâ;</hi> nor can any Creature or Authority upon Earth legally diſſolve this Bond, or ſuperſede this <hi>Commiſſion,</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs it be in caſe of a <hi>Criminal</hi> forfeiture,
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:64639:44"/>as was that of <hi>Abiathar,</hi> 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 2.26, 27. or of a Natural or Moral Incapaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of diſcharging the Duties, and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwering the Ends of the Office. The Reaſon is plain; becauſe the Office and Commiſſion is primarily, and fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally from God, and not from man. Neither may any one that is lawfully called to, and inveſted with it, voluntarily deſert, or alienate himſelf from it, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the dreadful guilt of Sacrilege, Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtacy, and Perjury: <hi>A diſpenſation of the Goſpel is committed unto me,</hi> ſays St. <hi>Paul, and a neceſſity is</hi> (thereby) <hi>laid upon me;</hi> therefore, <hi>Wo unto me, if I preach not the Goſpel,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.16, 17. As for any par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Exceptions in ſome rare and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary caſes:<note n="*" place="margin">See Mr. <hi>G. T.</hi> Paſtor's Care and Dig. <hi>p. 14.</hi>
                  </note> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in it may be lawful for a man to lay aſide his Miniſterial Function. I ſhall not here mention, nor ſhall I now ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine how far, and in what caſes it is both lawful, prudential, and expedient for the <hi>Churches</hi> peace and ſafety, to give way to the torrent of a Tide, and for a ſeaſon to ſuſpend the ordinary acts, and exerciſe of the Miniſtry; which is
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:64639:45"/>a caſe that hath been, and for ought we know, or for ought we have at God's hands deſerved, may again be.</p>
               <p>But I ſhall wave this Queſtion, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs I were particularly call'd to it, and ſhall conclude this <hi>Chapter,</hi> with the <hi>Sixth Petition</hi> of our LORD's <hi>Prayer: Lead us not into temptation, but deliver us from evil;</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb n="81" facs="tcp:64639:45"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. V.</hi> The Second Part of the Paſtor's Charge, <hi>viz.</hi> To govern and rule The Flock.</head>
               <p n="2">2. THE other, and indeed the more difficult and obnoxious part of our Miniſterial Work, is to rule, to exerciſe the Authority that is given us of the Lord, as Shepherds over his Flock.</p>
               <p>This was what I had neither time, nor mind to diſcourſe of in the Pulpit; and ſhould now diſmiſs it with the ſame brevity, and general hints (being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcious of my own weakneſs, and appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſive of the uſe that ſome are like to make of what I muſt ſay, if I ſay any thing) did not the ſenſe of my Duty ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lige me to accept of the Burthen that is laid upon me, and to diſcharge it with that ſincerity, and impartiality (accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the meaſure that is given me of
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:64639:46"/>God, for his Churches Service) as doth become one that deſires to be found faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful.</p>
               <p>I confeſs my heart cannot but ſhrink at the thoughts of entring into this rough and thorny Province, this Seat of War, where I ſee ſo many Parties en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gag'd, and Swords drawn at one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
               <p>God knows, and my Brethren are my Witneſſes, that this is not a Work of my own ſeeking; nor am I come as an Advocate of any of the contending par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, but with an earneſt deſire, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign of Peace and Truth: In the proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution whereof I ſhall purpoſely (as far as poſſible) decline any uſe of the ſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, or ſuffrages of ſuch as have been at ſharps on this Argument; and confine my ſelf to thoſe Oracles of the divinely inſpired and revealed Truth in the Holy Scriptures; the Rule which at laſt we muſt be determined by, if ever we be well determined. The word that God (this way) putteth in my mouth, that ſhall I ſpeak, as he ſhall pleaſe to give me underſtanding, and utterance: and
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:64639:46"/>let thoſe that are otherwiſe minded, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider before they cenſure.</p>
               <p>Should I pretend to aſſume the whole Queſtion of Church-government, it would ſwell into a volume; whereas I intend only this one ſhort <hi>Chapter,</hi> for what I ſhall now ſay on this Subject; and therein as little as I can; which yet to ſome perhaps may ſeem too much; and to others too little.</p>
               <p>I ſhall not ſpend any time in writing an Encomium of Government, either in general, or particular, which hath been done by many others, of the uſefulneſs and neceſſity, whereof the whole ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal world is experimentally ſenſible.</p>
               <p>But of Government there are divers kinds; according to the diverſity both of the matter and form of it.</p>
               <p>That which we are now to conſider, is the Eccleſiaſtical, or the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Church, and Houſe of God in the World. The <hi>Apoſtle</hi> tells us, <hi>There is no Power but of God; the Powers that be, are ordained of God. Who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever therefore reſiſteth, reſiſteth the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of God,</hi> Rom. 13.1, 2. The Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:64639:47"/>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Poteſtates.</hi> Governments that are amongſt men, are God's Ordinance, tho all the evil ways of climbing into it, and male-adminiſtration of it, or impru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent circumſtances in the conſtitution of it, be not of God, but of men. But if all the Powers and Governments of the world be of God, then hath he not left his Church, which is his peculiar King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, without Government. But the Queſtion is not, Whether Eccleſiaſtical Government in the general be <hi>jure divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no;</hi> but whether there be any particular Form of this Government that is ſo, and what that Form is.</p>
               <p>This is the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, the <hi>Nodus vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce dignus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There are ſome that deny there is any Form of Church-Government, appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of Chriſt under the New-Teſtament, but that it is left to be modified by the Rules of Human Prudence, and Diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: But then ſuch would do well to let us know when, and where, and to whom the Lord Jeſus Chriſt hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted this Power of <hi>Legiſlation,</hi> and eſtabliſhing the Forms of Government to his Churches. 'Tis true, there are
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:64639:47"/>ſome Circumſtantials of Government, that are, and muſt be left to the Diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Governors, to be adapted, <hi>pro re natâ,</hi> to the preſent ſtate of the Governed. But if the Eſſentials of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment be left to the wiſdom and will of men, then are the Churches in a very ill caſe. Nor do I know how we ſhall be able to prove, <hi>That as Moſes was faithful in all the houſe of God, as a ſervant, ſo Chriſt much more, as a ſon over his own houſe,</hi> Heb. 3. begin. But that he was ſo, <hi>de facto,</hi> in the buſineſs of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment and Diſcipline, as well as in Doctrine and Worſhip, and ſatisfaction to God, as our Redeemer, is well enough to be prov'd from the Scriptures. Whence I conclude, that the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Church is appointed of Chriſt in the Holy Scriptures, <hi>in ſpecie,</hi> as well as <hi>in genere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Of thoſe that are thus far agreed, there are yet divers Opinions, and Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties; ſome are for this Form of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; others for that; the Reaſons of which diſagreement are commonly ſome ſuch things as theſe.</p>
               <pb n="86" facs="tcp:64639:48"/>
               <p n="1">1ſt. <hi>An invincible ignorance of the true ſenſe of the Scriptures in this Point; and the very mind of Chriſt, and his Apoſtles in them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Charity obliges me to believe, that there are very many of moſt of the contending Parties, that would readily, and cheerfully acquieſce in the Senti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of their Oppoſers, could they but overcome the Reaſons, which they think they have truly and rightly drawn from the Scriptures, to be otherwiſe minded: And yet it is moſt certain, that there is groſs and affected ignorance enough a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Contenders of all ſides: And theſe are the perſons that are wont to be moſt fierce and confident. The mind of Chriſt is in it ſelf but one, and can be no more; therefore our diſagreement about it neceſſarily concludes our Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, or ſomething worſe on the one ſide, or the other.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>The natural fondneſs that men have for their own Ways and Luſts.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Though there is no Government in the World of ſo pure a nature, or firm
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:64639:48"/>a texture, or conſtitution, but that it may be abus'd to the ſervice of baſe ends, and private intereſt; yet there are ſome Modes and Forms of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that are in themſelves more dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctly accommodated, by the Policy of the Compilers, and Founders of them to ſuch purpoſes: And ſuch are they eſpecially, that are of mens deviſing, and obtruding on the Spiritual Kingdom of Chriſt. For Uſurpers (be ſure) will always frame their Laws, and Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thods, in favour of their own Deſigns: And were there nothing elſe but private Intereſt and Deſign among the Parties concern'd, that difference that is amongſt men, on this account, muſt needs be an occaſion of contention. But much more muſt ſuch as are acted by Principies of true Conſcience and Integrity, think themſelves bound to proteſt againſt all ſuch politick and carnal Forms of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>The Groſs Abuſe, and Degene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racy of a good and well ordered Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="88" facs="tcp:64639:49"/>
               <p>The pureſt and moſt durable Metal, if not well kept, will in length of time grow foul and ruſty, and look very un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like it ſelf, and then it will be queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on'd and quarrell'd at, and deny'd to be what in truth it is: And the ſame fate are the beſt Governments in the World ſubject to. As was the Kingly Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment among the <hi>Aſſyrians</hi> in the days of <hi>Sardanapalus;</hi> and among the <hi>Romans,</hi> in the days of <hi>Tarquinius Superbus:</hi> And ſo it hath been of ſeveral other Forms of Government amongſt men. The beſt and moſt ſacred Conſtitutions that ever were in the Earth, by their abuſe have fallen under the <hi>Odium</hi> and contempt of the more inconſiderate part, that are apt to luſt after new things, and know not how to reſtore the old to their Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal rectitude; as befel the <hi>Theocracy</hi> of God's own appointment, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 8.5 and 7. But were the Argument good from the abuſe of a thing againſt the uſe of it, 'twere eaſy to argue our ſelves into the groſſeſt Abſurdities in Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
               <p>Now if we would rightly underſtand what that Form of Government is, that
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:64639:49"/>Chriſt hath choſen for his Churches un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Goſpel, we muſt conſider what the Subject of the Government is, or the matter which is to be inform'd by it. 'Tis not enough to ſay the <hi>Church,</hi> which is <hi>vox ambigua;</hi> but we muſt di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh: Nor is it neceſſary for me to take notice here of all the Diſtinctions the Word is capable of, or that have been, by ſome others, impoſed on it. As,</p>
               <p n="1">1. The Church <hi>Oecumenical;</hi> to which the Pope ſo arrogantly and faſly lays a claim of Supremacy. Or,</p>
               <p n="2">2dly. The Church National; of which that Eminent Servant of Chriſt, Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> hath given ſo Rational, and Scriptural an account; and which (that I know) is not by any one, as yet, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered. Or,</p>
               <p n="3">3dly. The Church <hi>Provincial;</hi> which is the Conſtitution and Union of the particular Churches, within the limits of the Province, into one diſtinct Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litical Body, or Sacred Polity, under
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:64639:50"/>the general inſpection and Authority of one Eccleſiaſtical Head, either ſingle, or collective. Or,</p>
               <p n="4">4ly. The <hi>Presbyterial, Claſſical, Collegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate, Dioceſan, &amp;c.</hi> which I take as Synoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous, and includes all the particular <hi>Congregations</hi> within the bounds of ſuch a Diviſion. Or,</p>
               <p n="5">5ly. The <hi>Congregational,</hi> made up of one <hi>Paſtor,</hi> with his people, and neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary Officers.</p>
               <p>Theſe are the Diſtinctions given ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the <hi>Common Diviſion</hi> that hath, for <hi>Order</hi> ſake, been made of the Church.</p>
               <p>But the only Diſtinction which I ſhall now a little animadvert upon, is this;</p>
               <p>The Rulers of the Church, and the Ruled; and ſhall ſpeak to the Laſt firſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Ruled.</hi> And herein ſhall anſwer theſe three Queſtions.</p>
               <pb n="91" facs="tcp:64639:50"/>
               <list>
                  <item>1. Who they are they muſt be ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led.</item>
                  <item>2. By whom they muſt be ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led.</item>
                  <item>3. By What Laws they muſt be ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led.</item>
               </list>
               <p>Q. 1. <hi>Who they are that muſt be ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>S.</hi> The Anſwer, in general, is what <hi>Paul</hi> gives; <hi>loco cit.</hi> Rom. 13.1. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>every Soul.</hi> He that is not ſubject to the good <hi>Government</hi> of that <hi>Political</hi> Body, civil, or ſacred, whereunto he ſtands related as a Member, and by which he ought to be comprehended, is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> the Lawleſs and Diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedient, for whom the Bridle and the Rod of the Law is made; and ſo both Rulers and Ruled are equally ſubject to the Laws, though not the ſame Laws of Government; but according to the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent capacities, orders, and Relation wherein they are placed in the Oecono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my of the Church. Though the <hi>Rulers</hi> and the <hi>Ruled</hi> cannot be the ſame, <hi>ſub codem reſpectu;</hi> yet in divers reſpects they may, and ought; Thoſe that are Rulers of ſome, muſt be ruled by others: So then the Ruled part, of which I am firſt to ſpeak, is twofold; the Clergy and the Laity; or the Miniſters and the
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:64639:51"/>People; according to the duplicity of the Government; to which, as Church-Members they ſtand related; which is either general and common, or ſpecial and proper.</p>
               <p>The Rulers and Officers of the Church, as thoſe of Armies, and Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealths or Kingdoms, are, or ought to be <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>men under Authority,</hi> and the Laws of a Polity, that is proper to them as ſuch, as well as the people, whom they govern by the Laws that are fitted for them: I ſay, under Authority, and that not only, and immediately unto Chriſt, but alſo unto men; even ſuch as Chriſt, the Supream Legiſlator, and Lord, hath Commiſſioned to rule for, and under him, in his Church. This ſeems to me to have been one great miſtake, and the ground of a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand more; That the Miniſters of the Goſpel have, and hold their Authority in the Church, only from Chriſt <hi>in capite;</hi> ſo as to conclude an equality, and co-ordination of Paſtors. 'Tis true, the general Patent and Grant of the Office is originally, and immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately from Chriſt; but the particular
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:64639:51"/>diſtribution of Commiſſion is not ſo, but from ſuch hands as are entruſted and authorized by him to beſtow it on others; and unto whom, they that receive it, ought to be accountable for their well, or male-adminiſtration of it. All thoſe that are duly qualify'd, and call'd to the Miniſtry, are equally Miniſters of Chriſt, <hi>i. e.</hi> one is not more a Miniſter than another; nor meerly, as ſuch, have they greater power one than another; as all men in the World are equally men, God's Creatures, and partakers of Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Nature: But from hence to deny a ſubordination of one to another, in point of Government, is to pluck up all Government in the World by the roots, and turn the whole Creation into Anarchy, and worſe than its firſt <hi>Tohn vebohu;</hi> which is one of the maddeſt Principles that ever was ſuggeſted to the Rational Nature, by that grand Author of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion. Let it be conſidered, that the Officers of the Church of Chriſt, or the Clergy, as for diſtinction they are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly call'd, are a particular diſtinct Company and Society of men, as the People or Layity are another; and ſo
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:64639:52"/>they ever were, and were to be accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by God's own appointment, both under the Old and New-Teſtament: And as it is in all regulated Armies, and other ſecular Governments in the world, the Officers are a ſeparate Political Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and Community of themſelves, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct from the reſt; and if ſo, then they ought to have their proper Polity and Government as ſuch: a Government peculiar and diſtinct from that of the common people, and which is call'd Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erarchy, only <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. And that it ever hath been, and always muſt be ſo, is not hard to prove.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>That it hath been ever ſo,</hi> ſince Chriſt hath had a Church upon the Earth; I ſay a Church, organically con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted, and politically govern'd. Such was the Jews under that of the hands of <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron;</hi> That the Miniſters under the Old Teſtament, the Prieſts and Levites, were a diſtinct Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, yea, and to avoid confuſion, a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct Tribe, purpoſely ſo choſen of God; and that they had their diſtinct Polity and Government, of God's own appointing, and that with a great deal
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:64639:52"/>of caution and particularity, even to very minute circumſtances, in all the Orders, Degrees, and Courſes of their Conſecration, and Miniſtration. I would think it needleſs for me to ſpend time to demonſtrate; Thoſe that have any acquaintance with the Sacred Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of that Church, cannot be ignorant of this. And this was both the beauty, and the ſtrength and ſecurity of that Church: the Hedge that God made about his Vineyard. And as they were a diſtinct Body, as <hi>Clergy,</hi> ſeparate from all the other Tribes; ſo they had their proper Government and Oeconomy; the <hi>Prieſts</hi> of the Houſe of <hi>Aaron,</hi> the Rulers; and the reſt of the <hi>Levites</hi> the Ruled. And that it was ſo under the Goſpel too from the beginning, is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry evident. Our bleſſed LORD, when he began, with his Miniſtry, to lay the Foundations of the new <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> the Goſpel Church, what could be more plainly diſtinguiſhing, than his chuſing the ſelect number of <hi>Twelve,</hi> as one Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periour Order of Miniſters; and of <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venty,</hi> whom he ſent forth to Preach the Goſpel, as an Order inferiour to
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:64639:53"/>the <hi>Twelve?</hi> Tho' their general Office and Commiſſion, as Preachers, were both the ſame, which made them of one Body and Society as ſuch, but of a diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Order and Degree; and theſe as plainly and politically diſtinguiſhed from the Body of the common Diſciples, as any one political Society, or Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of Men in the World is from another. And thus they have been ever ſince, with all the reaſon in the World, taken as a particular Company and Body of Men, on the account of their Holy Calling, ſeparate and diſtinct from the Common People; and as ſuch, have a Government, of Chriſts own Inſtitution, proper and peculiar to them. I do not think that the exact number of <hi>Twelve,</hi> or of <hi>Seventy,</hi> doth at all concern us Gentiles; but that which is in it com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon both to Jews and Gentiles concerns us as well as them. What the <hi>Prieſts</hi> were to the <hi>Levites,</hi> that the <hi>Twelve</hi> were to the <hi>Seventy.</hi> Yea and among the <hi>Twelve</hi> there ſeems to be a difference both of Order and Degree. Tho' <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> was not the <hi>Princeps Apoſtolorum,</hi> he was the <hi>Primus Diſcipulorum,</hi> the Seniour
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:64639:53"/>of that School, or <hi>Collegium Presbytero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum,</hi> and next in Dignity, under Chriſt his LORD and Maſter; for we find that <hi>Peter</hi> was the Perſon, unto whom Chriſt did immediately direct all his Speeches that concerned them in common: that when the <hi>Twelve,</hi> or any part of them are mention'd, if <hi>Peter</hi> were one, he was always named firſt. Yea, and <hi>Matthew,</hi> in his Catalogue, does not only name him firſt, but gives him the Title of <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, which, for ought I know, is as much as <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, or <hi>Praeſes.</hi> Neither, tho' this be granted, will it at all ſtrengthen, or favour the arrogant claim of the Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> to be <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi>'s Succeſſor. For <hi>Peter</hi> himſelf was call'd the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, not with relation to the Church Univerſal, of which Chriſt alone is the Head; but with relation to that particular Society, or <hi>Collegium,</hi> of which he was then a Member. For when the frame and Oeconomy of that particular Society was diſſolved, as it was by the Death of Chriſt, <hi>Peter</hi> was no more a <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, a <hi>Primate</hi> or <hi>Preſident,</hi> than any of the other <hi>Eleven</hi> were.</p>
               <pb n="98" facs="tcp:64639:54"/>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>That it muſt be always ſo.</hi> And great reaſon there is for this.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Becauſe Chriſt hath inſtituted it by his own practice, and example, as appears by what hath been now ſaid; and what Chriſt hath once inſtituted, may not by man be abrogated, or al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Becauſe there is perpetual need of it: I need not deſcant upon this; Dole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Experience tells us, to our ſhame, that there is no Society, or Body of men in the World, that have more need of the Reins of Government, than the Miniſtry. Hath every Company of Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicians, Chirurgeons, Merchants, Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thecaries, Taylors, Drapers, Shoema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers, Victuallers, Vintners, Bakers, Brick-layers. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> need of a Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment peculiar to their reſpective Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies and Profeſſions, in the beſt go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verned Towns and Corporations? I would I could ſay, that Miniſters have not much more; whoſe Errours and Miſcarriages are of ſadder conſequence than any of theirs aforementioned. If every Miniſter, as ſuch, be immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly under Chriſt, as to Government,
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:64639:54"/>(which cannot be, unleſs they had their Commiſſion immediately from him, as the Apoſtles, had) then is he account<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to none elſe, but is abſolute and independent in his Office. What groſſer principle of Tyranny can there be than this? What wider Gate can there be open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the moſt Licentious Arbitrarineſs? And in what a caſe then are the poor Churches? This is to pull down one Tyrant, and to ſet up many thouſands, and to make every <hi>Novice</hi> a Lord over Gods Heritage.</p>
               <p>Queſt. 2. <hi>By whom muſt they be ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sol.</hi> Not by themſelves ſure, that's plain <hi>Anarchy,</hi> and utterly inconſiſtent with any <hi>Form</hi> of Political Government; (which the <hi>Quakers</hi> themſelves would ſoon be weary of (as in <hi>Penſilvania,</hi> they ſay, they begin to be) were they not, in deſpight of their irrational Principles, preſerv'd from the miſchievous conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences of them by the common be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of the Government they here live under) but they muſt be rul'd by the Authority, which God hath ſet over them, and every one, both Paſtors and
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:64639:55"/>People, by their own immediate Officers. <hi>Obey them that have the rule over you, and ſubmit your ſelves, Heb.</hi> 13.17. And who are they whom Chriſt hath ſet to Rule and to Govern in his Houſe; but thoſe whom he calls his <hi>Stewards</hi> his Miniſters, into whoſe hands he hath committed the <hi>Keys</hi> of Government? Neither hath he ſhared the Ruling Power, or any part of it between them and the People; nor could it have been conſiſtent with the honour of his Wiſdom, or the Intereſt and Peace of his Churches to have done it. <hi>I will give unto Thee</hi> (not one, but both) <hi>the Keys of the Kingdom of Heaven, Mat.</hi> 16.19. That theſe are the <hi>Keys</hi> of Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine and Diſcipline, appears by the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of it in the next words. <hi>What<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever thou ſhalt bind on Earth, ſhall be bound in Heaven,</hi> which is the exerciſe of the Authority given him. Neither is this Power of Government given to <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> excluſively, nor as a private Diſciple, but as a publick Miniſter, and publick Officer in the Church of Chriſt; and with him to all the reſt of his Brethren in the ſame Office, for them and for their Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors, <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.18. Who is it that Chriſt means by the <hi>faithful and wiſe Steward? Lu.</hi>
                  <pb n="101" facs="tcp:64639:55"/>12.42. Is it not the ſame, that the Apoſtle means, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.1. <hi>The Miniſters of Chriſt;</hi> and <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.7. <hi>A Biſhop muſt be blameleſs, as the Steward of God.</hi> And this is the <hi>Steward, whom his Lord ſhall make Ruler over his Houſhold, to give them their portion of meat in due ſeaſon.</hi> So that the Government of his Church is eſtabliſhed by Chriſt, in the hands of his Miniſters, on whom he breathed the Holy-Ghoſt, to qualifie them for, and carry them thro' all the work, both or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary and extraordinary, whereto he ſent them, <hi>Joh.</hi> 20.22. By this it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears in the general, in whoſe hands, immediately under Chriſt, the govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing power doth lye; not in the People, but in the Miniſters of the Goſpel, who alone are his <hi>Stewards,</hi> and unto whom, at his departure, he delivered the <hi>Keys</hi> of his Houſe, and of all the Proviſions and Treaſures in it. And who are ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, in the New Teſtament, call'd his <hi>Ambaſſadors,</hi> or <hi>Meſſengers;</hi> ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times <hi>Biſhops,</hi> or <hi>Overſeers;</hi> ſometimes <hi>Presbyters,</hi> or <hi>Elders;</hi> ſometimes <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſtotes,</hi> or <hi>Rulers,</hi> which are but ſeveral Names and Titles given to one and the
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:64639:56"/>ſame ſort of men. I know no point in Scripture more plainly aſſerted, than this, <hi>viz.</hi> That Chriſt hath join'd the Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Ruling Authority together, and committed it, in conjunction, to the ſame hands. But what God hath join<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed together, let no man put aſunder.</p>
               <p>Queſt. 3. <hi>By what Laws muſt they be ruled?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sol.</hi> Not by Laws of mens deviſing; which they are wont to accommodate to the ſervice of their own Inclinations and Ends; but by the written Laws of his own preſcription. The Oeconomy is Spiritual and Divine, and ſo muſt the Laws be, by which it is adminiſtred. <hi>Other Foundation can no man lay, than that is laid, which is Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.11. The Foundation of Government and Diſcipline, as well as of Doctrine and Worſhip, is laid by Jeſus Chriſt; and whoever lays any other Foundation in either of theſe, entrenches on Chriſt's Prerogative, and ſhall do it to his own peril. Tho' in the <hi>neceſſary Circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tials</hi> of all theſe, humane Prudence and Authority hath a determining power, for the Order, Peace, and Edification
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:64639:56"/>of the Church; but not to its deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or diſturbance. I ſay, the <hi>neceſſary Circumſtantials;</hi> but unneceſſarily to multiply Circumſtantials, under the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Indifferents, and on pretence of Decency or Authority, is a very unaccep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, and offenſive piece of Superſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and to impoſe them, as the indiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſible terms of Communion, on ſuch as are not ſatisfied about them, is not the leaſt Inſtance of Church-Tyranny. Church Officers are but Chriſt's Depu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and not Lords of Gods Heritage; and therefore muſt rule by Chriſt's Laws; <hi>For he is our Judge, our Law-giver, and our King, Iſa.</hi> 33.22. Our Power is but to execute; 'tis he that muſt make, and give the Laws. And what theſe Laws are, and where to be found, I need not ſay the Holy Scriptures are his <hi>Statute-Book;</hi> If they ſpeak not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to this Rule, it is becauſe there is no light in them.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>The Rulers.</hi> If there be ſome to be ruled, there muſt be others to Rule. <hi>Relata ſe ſimul ponunt &amp; tollunt; &amp; qui novit unum Relatorum, novit &amp; alterum.</hi> Yet here it will be enquired, who are thoſe that are to Rule?</p>
               <pb n="104" facs="tcp:64639:57"/>
               <p>I ſhall not take notice of the Regal Power, or how far, it being Chriſtian, it extends both over Paſtors and Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, not only as Civil Subjects, but as Chriſtian Churches; and not only in the things of men, but in the things of God; but ſhall refer my Reader for this to Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> of National Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, and to others that have written of it, it being forreign to my preſent Text. But as Paſtors and People are two di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct Political Bodies, ſo there muſt be two diſtinct <hi>Forms</hi> of Government proper to each of them. I ſhall ſpeak,</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Of the People.</hi> Theſe are to be rul'd, and not to rule in the Houſe of God. I know this is an hard ſaying, and that there are many that can badly bear it; nor would I thus diſpleaſe them, could I help it, and yet be faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful. Thoſe that are for a <hi>Democracy,</hi> ſeem to be guided by the ſame Spirit, as they were, <hi>Numb.</hi> 16.3. <hi>Who gather<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed themſelves together againſt</hi> Moſes <hi>and againſt</hi> Aaron, <hi>and ſaid unto them, ye take too much upon you, ſeeing all the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation is holy, every one of them. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore then lift ye up your ſelves above the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:64639:57"/>of the LORD?</hi> That the Tribe of <hi>Reuben</hi> ſhould be guilty of ſuch a thing was not ſo ſtrange; but great pity it was, that any of the Tribe of <hi>Levi</hi> ſhould conſpire with them. There is no Miniſter of Jeſus Chriſt, that can conſent to ſuch an Uſurpation, and be innocent, and true to the Truſt, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to him. Let thoſe that are for the Peoples ruling in the Church of Chriſt, ſhew us when and where the <hi>Keys</hi> of Government, or any one of them, was put into any of their hands. Where did our LORD make them partners with us in the Government of his Church? Or what part of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verning Office and Work was it that he aſſigned to them? Herein I am ſorry that I muſt diſſent, not only from Men of an inferiour Note, and more Hete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rodox Principles, but from the Learned <hi>Calvin</hi> too, and almoſt all that follow him. For I could never yet find in Scripture any ſuch Officer as a non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preaching ruling Elder, appointed of Chriſt, or of his Apoſtles in the Church. The one and only Officer that Chriſt himſelf made, was the <hi>Miniſter</hi> of his
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:64639:58"/>Word, the Evangelical Paſtor, whoſe work was to feed and to rule the Flock. To which the Apoſtles afterward added the Office of the <hi>Deacons,</hi> as Servants to them, and Helps in the meaner part of their work, as may be ſeen, <hi>Act.</hi> 6. <hi>begin.</hi> and as <hi>Moſes</hi> did, for the eaſe of his Government, by the advice of <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thro, Exod.</hi> 18.18, &amp;c. Which, tho' it be Apoſtolical, yet cannot be ſaid to be <hi>Primarily,</hi> but only <hi>Secundarily Jure Divino.</hi> The Scriptures that are alledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in favour of this Ruling Lay Elder, do not (as I think) prove any ſuch con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſions; which I ſhall now examine, and leave all to the conſideration of ſuch, as can without prejudice, weigh what I am now bold to offer. One Text we have, <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.6, 7, 8. To which I have this exception. If the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>He that ruleth</hi> be here mention'd as a diſtinct Officer in the Church, then why not all the reſt? of which we have theſe ſeven in this one Scripture, <hi>viz.</hi> he that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſieth: he that miniſtreth: he that teacheth: he that exhorteth: he that giveth: he that ruleth: and he that ſheweth mercy. But if we go to work
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:64639:58"/>in this way, how will Offices be multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied in the Church, beyond all that was ever intended or imagined? And then, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.28, 29, 30. where we have no leſs than nine mention'd, among which we find <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, which they would have to ſignifie the <hi>Ruling Lay-Elder;</hi> and ſo we would believe too, could they prove, that all the reſt here mentioned were ſo many Offices in the Church. They inſiſt very confidently on theſe words of ſanction, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>God hath ſet</hi> and appointed; but why this word, which hath undeniably an equal relation to all, ſhould make, or prove one to be an Office, and not another, I confeſs is a depth that I am not able to fathom. Here (as I think) the great miſtake lies; that Gifts and Offices are confounded. The Apoſtle 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.4, 5, 6. very plainly diſtinguiſhes between <hi>Gifts, Adminiſt ations,</hi> and <hi>Operations,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Where by Gifts are meant the Abilities beſtowed upon the Offices, or Adminiſtrations in order to the operations, or effects of them, to the edifying of the Church. Now in the fore-mention'd Scriptures
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:64639:59"/>we find a diverſity of Gifts and Opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; but Gifts and Offices are not the ſame.</p>
               <p>But there is one Scripture more, which hath been already quoted, on the Doctrinal part of this Diſcourſe, which ſeems to ſpeak more fully to their pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, and to make a diſtinction between Preaching and Ruling Elders, <hi>viz.</hi> 1 Tim. 5.17. <hi>Let the Elders that Rule well be accounted worthy of double honour, eſpecially they who labour in the Word and Doctrine.</hi> Much uſe hath been made of this Text to little purpoſe; I ſhall not now mention any of all that I have ſeen, and read of it; but give you, as God hath enabled me, the true ſenſe of this Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and let the unprejudiced Reader judge.</p>
               <p>And that we may underſtand the mind of Chriſt in it, we will conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,</p>
               <p n="1">1. By whom, and to whom this Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection was given.</p>
               <p>It was by the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> the great planter of the <hi>Churches</hi> of the <hi>Gentiles;</hi> and who, as an Apoſtle, had Power and Authority to order and determine all
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:64639:59"/>the affairs that concern'd the Diſcipline and Government of the Churches of his own planting. Both this, and the other Epiſtle was written by him to <hi>Timothy,</hi> whom he left as his Subſtitute, or Surro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate with Apoſtolical Power under him in the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Epheſus,</hi> to ordain <hi>Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters</hi> as there ſhould be occaſion, and to diſpoſe of the Dignities and Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nues of the Church to ſuch as were moſt worthy of them, and would beſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove them to the Glory of Chriſt, and the Churches benefit. And for the ſame end it was that he left <hi>Titus</hi> in <hi>Crete,</hi> as his Subſtitute, or Overſeer in that Iſland, as appears <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.5. So that this advice was not ſent to the people, nor to the Inferior <hi>Presbyters,</hi> who were to be or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered by it, but to one in a higher Sphear of Authority, and by whom they were to be ordered; whether for diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction ſake he be called Evangeliſt, or Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, or Preſident, or Moderator; the difference is but verbal.</p>
               <p n="2">2. What doth the Apoſtle mean by the <hi>double honour</hi> here?</p>
               <p>There are two things that ſeem to bid fair for the Senſe, which will both come to one in the iſſue.</p>
               <pb n="110" facs="tcp:64639:60"/>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>The Honour of Maintenance:</hi> and ſo we find the word ſometimes uſed in Scripture; as <hi>ver.</hi> 3. of this <hi>Chap. Matt.</hi> 15.6. <hi>Acts</hi> 28 10. and the following words of the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> in this Scripture, ſeem to look this way: and then the Senſe muſt be this: Let thoſe Officers of the Church that beſt diſcharge the Duties of their Office in ruling, but e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially in Preaching (which is the more noble and neceſſary part of their Work) have the greateſt encouragement on this kind; <hi>i e.</hi> Let not the Revenues of the Church (which were then but ſmall and uncertain) be beſtowed promiſcuouſly, much leſs partially, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>; but ſo as may beſt ſubſerve the Churches good Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, and the grand Deſign of preaching the Goſpel.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>The Honour of Authority and Obedience.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And this is the prime ſenſe of the Word, as it is uſed in the Fifth Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment; <hi>Honour thy Father, and thy Mother,</hi> Exod. 20.12. is the ſame with, <hi>Obey your Parents,</hi> Eph. 6.1. <hi>And obey them that have the rule over you,</hi> Heb. 13.17. and ſo is the word uſed, <hi>Heb.</hi> 5.4.
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:64639:60"/>
                  <hi>No man taketh this Honour unto himſelf:</hi> i. e. this Office, this Dignity, this power and authority</p>
               <p>And this indeed is much more wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily and properly call'd Honour, than a rich worldly Revenue, or a fat Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice or Biſhoprick (things unborn in thoſe days) which men too often abuſe, both to God's diſhonour, and their own.</p>
               <p>Now if this be the Double Honour here intended, as to me ſeems moſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable; at leaſt, that it is included, as the moſt eminent part of it; then the ſenſe will be this: Let thoſe Presbyters or Miniſters that appear, on experience and tryal, to have a Spirit of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; but eſpecially with it, an emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nency of ability and diligence in preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Word, be made Rulers, and Superintendents over the inferior part of the <hi>Clergy;</hi> let ſuch be taken into the <hi>Collegium, Presbyterorum regens;</hi> the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gency of the Church. So that it is not the diſtinction of Office, but the quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication of the Officer, that the Apoſtle gives this direction for.</p>
               <p n="3">3. We muſt conſider the perſons, on whom this double honour is to be
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:64639:61"/>conferr'd; or who are thus to be digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied as the word <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, properly ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies; and theſe are Elders; deſcrib'd,
<list>
                     <item>1. <hi>In genere;</hi> by their Office.</item>
                     <item>2. <hi>In ſpecie;</hi> by their Qualifications.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>By their general Office,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, which is a word always us'd to denote the Miniſters of the Word in the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel-Church; as <hi>Act.</hi> 11.30. <hi>ch.</hi> 14.23. <hi>ch.</hi> 15.2, 6, 22, 23. <hi>ch.</hi> 16.4. <hi>ch.</hi> 20.17. <hi>ch.</hi> 21.18. <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.5. <hi>Jam.</hi> 5.14. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.1. 2 <hi>Ep. John</hi> 1. and <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 3.1.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>By their ſpecial Qualification;</hi> which is double.</p>
               <p n="1">1. They much be ſuch as <hi>Rule well;</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, which is another Title, peculiarly given in the New Teſtament, to the Miniſters of the Word, whoſe Office it is to Rule as well as to Preach.</p>
               <p n="2">2. They muſt be <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, ſuch as <hi>labour in the Word and Doctrine.</hi> So that the word <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, doth not diſtinguiſh, as I have ſaid, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween two Offices; but between the twofold Qualifications of one and the ſame Office. There were in the Church
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:64639:61"/>of <hi>Epheſus</hi> (which was a Collegiate, or Presbyterial Church) many Presbyters, the Talent of whoſe Gifts lay diverſly, as we find it doth in all other Churches; ſome were fitter for Government, others for Preaching; ſome excelled in one Gift, others in another. Now the Apoſtle adviſes <hi>Timothy</hi> how to make his choice of Perſons for Government in the Presbytery; whom to prefer to, and entruſt with a double honour, or higher degree of Dignity and Power in this kind and ſphere of Government; and tells him, they muſt be ſuch, as have behav'd themſelves well in the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoral Government of their particular Flocks and Congregations; and eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially ſuch of them as are moſt eminent and laborious in Preaching the Word; whereby they purchaſe to themſelves a good Degree; as it is ſaid of the <hi>Deacons,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim</hi> 3.13. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, a place of higher Honour and Truſt, from a Deacon to a Presbyter from a Presbyter to a Preſident. Preferments ought to be diſpenſed according to every ones Qualifications and Merits. Whence it appears, that there are Degrees in the
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:64639:62"/>Miniſterial Office: And this is that the Apoſtle here gives this Direction about; not at all countenancing a Non-Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Ruling Lay-Elder; but diſcounte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nancing a Lordly, Lazy, Non-Preaching Biſhop, or Superintendent. That the Preaching Elder or Miniſter of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel is to Rule, as well as to Preach the Word, is ſo plainly aſſerted in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, that, I think, cannot by any be denied. But if this Ruling Power were divided by Chriſt, or his Apoſtles, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <hi>Them</hi> and the <hi>People,</hi> or any <hi>part</hi> of the People; can any one give us a reaſon, why neither Chriſt nor his Apoſtles ſhould ever ſpeak a word, to direct us, how the Diviſion of this Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Power muſt be made? What muſt be their part, and what ours? How they muſt be qualified, as well as we? and the Deacons, for which they were careful to give the neceſſary Rules? Yea and how they muſt be maintain'd too? For to lay the burden of an Office on a Man, and to make no proviſion for his Mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, ſeems hard, and not very honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable to him whoſe Servant he pretends to be; eſpecially conſidering, that they
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:64639:62"/>could not but know and foreſee, how tender all Men naturally are in the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Honour and Maintenance; and of what miſchievous conſequence the leaving ſuch a Queſtion as this in the dark, and undetermined, would be: That it would involve the Church in endleſs ſtrifes, and quarrels, and confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions. But will the Lay-Elder lay his Claim to a Maintenance, from that word in the Text, <hi>viz. double Honour;</hi> taking it for the Honour of <hi>Maintenance?</hi> Let him then read on the next verſe there; <hi>For the Scripture ſaith, Thou ſhalt not muzzle the Oxe that treadeth out the Corn: And the labourer is worthy of his reward.</hi> The firſt of theſe Scriptures you have, <hi>Deut.</hi> 25.4. which the Apoſtle makes uſe of, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.9. And you may ſee how he there applies it, only to the Miniſters of the Goſpel; <hi>Thoſe that ſow unto the People ſpiritual things;</hi> v. 11. <hi>That miniſter about holy things, and wait at the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar;</hi> v. 13. The other Scripture you have, <hi>Matth.</hi> 10.10. <hi>The work-man is worthy of his meat:</hi> Which are Chriſt's own words to the Twelve, when he ſent them forth to Preach the Goſpel.
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:64639:63"/>Here's never a word of the Ruling El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der in all this, nor any proviſion made for him. And this one thing is enough to clear the ſenſe of the precedent verſe, that there is no ſuch thing as the Ruling, Non Preaching Elder intended in it; but the double Honour is for thoſe that tread out the Corn, and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour in the LORD's Harveſt in Word and Doctrine. And theſe are the only Perſons ſpoken of in that, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.17.</p>
               <p>So then; The Rulers of the People are their Paſtors, who are to Rule, eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one over his own particular Flock, or Congregation, in the things of God, and of their Souls; who, for the eaſe of their Government, and the advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of their Miniſterial work, have warrant from Scripture to ordain and appoint Deacons under them, and other neceſſary ſervile Officers, who derive their power immediately from their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor; are accountable to him; and may, and ought to be deſpos'd by him in caſe of Male-adminiſtration; as every Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain in an Army; Every Mayor in a Corporation; every Maſter in a Family have the proper power over their own
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:64639:63"/>Companies, Burroughs, and Families, and all the inferiour Officers in them, to diſpoſe and govern them for their good, according to the known and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Laws of that Superiour Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, under which they live, and unto which they themſelves are accountable.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>The Rulers of the Paſtors or Officers of the Church.</hi> I am very apprehenſive that this is a tender Point, wherein, I even tremble to think, that I muſt be either ſinfully ſilent, or declare my diſſent from ſo many of my dear Brethren, whom I know to be otherwiſe Orthodox, Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, Pious, and with whom I dare not compare my ſelf. But I have ſaid, and O that daiſy and doleful Experience did not proclaim it to the World, to the grief of ſome, and the ſhame of others, that there is no Company, or Society of Men in the World, that have more need of the ſtricteſt Government, than the Men of our Function; without which, we are, of all Mankind, in this reſpect, the moſt miſerable; and the poor Church of Chriſt in the forelorneſt caſe of any of God's Creatures upon Earth. But certainly he that hath ſo provided
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:64639:64"/>for the Government of the Kingdoms of the World, hath not left his own myſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Kingdom, wherein ſo much of his ſpecial intereſt lies, without ſuch a Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, as is every way adequate to all the parts and concerns of it. He that hath taken ſuch care to incloſe and fence out the wild <hi>Commons</hi> of the World, hath not deſign'd to leave his own <hi>Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den</hi> uninclos'd; Nor his <hi>Vineyard</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a <hi>Hedge</hi> about it, and a <hi>Wine-preſs</hi> and a <hi>Tower</hi> in it.</p>
               <p>How weak and inſatisfactory is this, to ſay, that we are all the Miniſters of Jeſus Chriſt, and Brethren to one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; that we have our Commiſſion, as Miniſters of the Goſpel, from him (tho' not immediately from him, which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, if it were ſo, would alter the caſe) who is the Supream Legiſlator? That we have our Bibles in our hands, and therein the unalterable Rules of our ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration, both in Doctrine, Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip and Diſcipline; the Laws, by which we are to Govern both our ſelves and the Churches; that we have the promiſe of the Holy Spirit to guide us into all truth; and an Unction from the Holy
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:64639:64"/>One, and know all things; that our Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice and Work is Sacred and Divine; of God and not of Men; alas! will all this make us Infallible, or Abſolute and Independent; exempt from all Laws and Bonds of an Eccleſiaſtical Polity; were we made the Miniſters of Chriſt to rule, and not to be rul'd? O that men would conſider the diſmal conſequents of ſuch an Hypotheſis, which I delight not now to aggravate.</p>
               <p>But if there muſt be a Government among Paſtors, conſider'd as a diſtinct Body from the People; then, it will be ſaid, there cannot be an equality, the Notion of Co-ordination of Paſtors and Churches is ſubverted, this being incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent with Government. But let wiſe Men conſider what that is that muſt needs lye at the bottom of this Levelling Principle. And yet Government doth not deſtroy the Equality and Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordination of Paſtors, or Churches, as ſuch, or <hi>per ſe;</hi> but only <hi>ſecundum quid;</hi> or in reſpect of Order; <hi>e. g.</hi> All the Captains in an Army, as Captains, are equal; ſo are all the Collonels, and all the other Officers, that are of one and
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:64639:65"/>the ſame Order; but between a Captain and a Collonel, there is an inequality: And as it is in a well Regimented Army; ſo it is in the Church of Chriſt, which is as an <hi>Army with Banners, Cant</hi> 6.10. And 'tis ſuppoſed too, that this ſubordination of Paſtors and Churches will conclude a neceſſity of a Supream Papal Head and Governour. This I take to be the great ſtumbling-block; the plain ſenſe where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of is but this; That if every Miniſter be not allowed to be a Pope over his own Congregation, then there muſt be one Pope over all the Congregations and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors in the Chriſtian World. Both which extreams are equally wide from the Truth, and perhaps equally pernicious to the Church. But to defend the Truth from both the <hi>Horns</hi> of this <hi>Dilemma,</hi> we will examine what is the true Scripture notions of a Church.</p>
               <p>We find in Scripture that the Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es which the Apoſtles planted, are reck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned by the great Towns, or Cities, which they choſe to begin to gather their Churches in, as appears both by the names that are given them, and by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring <hi>Act.</hi> 14.23. with <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.5. where
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:64639:65"/>the ordinary Elders in every <hi>Church,</hi> is the ſame with Ordaining Elders in every <hi>City.</hi> Neither do we find any Organical Church of the Apoſtles founding, any where mention'd in the New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but it bears the name of the Town or City, in which it was; beſides thoſe Domeſtick Churches of <hi>Priſcilla</hi> and <hi>Aquila,</hi> of <hi>Nymphas</hi> and <hi>Philemon,</hi> which were equivocally call'd Churches, becauſe ſome Congregations of the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers did either occaſionally, or ſtated<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly aſſemble to worſhip God there; or, as others think, becauſe all of theſe Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies were converted to Chriſtianity, and ſo became Churches or Houſes of God, which is little to our preſent Queſtion. Beſides, theſe Churches, thus planted by the Apoſtles in Towns and Cities, did ſtill retain their firſt names and ſingula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity: For one may always obſerve, that where the Scripture ſpeaks of the Churches of a whole Province, or Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, it ſpeaks of them as of different and diſtinct Churches, in the plural number, as the Churches of <hi>Judea,</hi> 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.14. the Churches of <hi>Aſia,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 16.19. the Churches of <hi>Syria</hi> and <hi>Cilicia, Act.</hi> 15.41.
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:64639:66"/>the Churches of <hi>Galatia,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 16.1. and <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.2. and the Churches of <hi>Macedonia,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8. 1. becauſe all theſe were large Countries, in which were many great Towns and Cities, in which the Churches were diſtinctly planted; and according to which they had their names and number. But when it ſpeaks of the Chriſtians in one Town, or City, it ſpeaks of them as one Church, in the ſingular; as the Church of <hi>Jeruſalem, Act.</hi> 8.1. the Church of <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioch, Act.</hi> 13.1. the Church of <hi>Corinth,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.2. So when the Churches of <hi>Aſia</hi> are ſpoken of together, they are the ſeven Churches, according to the number and names of the ſeven great Cities of <hi>Aſia,</hi> in which theſe Churches were planted; but when written to ſingly, it is the Church of <hi>Epheſus,</hi> and the Church of <hi>Smyrna,</hi> and the Church of <hi>Sardis, &amp;c.</hi> And it is to be obſerved,</p>
               <p n="1">1. That this account never once fails in all the New Teſtament, which proves that it is not ſpoken indifferently, but induſtriouſly, and for our inſtruction.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That Churches were thus reckon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the times of <hi>John,</hi> when he was in <hi>Patmos,</hi> which was 64 years after
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:64639:66"/>Chriſt; in all which time, it is incre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dible, that all the Chriſtians, in one of theſe great Cities, were no more than would make up one Congregation.</p>
               <p n="3">3. That there is no mention in the Scripture of any Churches planted in the Countreys adjacent to theſe Cities and Towns; yet it is rational to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, that there were many Converts, and ſome Congregations too in the Country-Villages, as well as in the great Towns; and therefore that theſe made up but one Church with that of the Town or City. Hence I conclude, that (theſe things being written by the inſpiration of the Holy Ghoſt, for our admonition) a Church, and a Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion are, in the language, and account of Scripture, two things. And that it is very unreaſonable and unwarrantable to alter the firſt Conſtitution or De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomination of the Churches, as they were left us by the Apoſtles, as far as they went, and therein a Rule given us to do the like. 'Tis true, the Univerſal Church was once but one ſingle Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and from which all the other Churches ſprang, as ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:64639:67"/>Daughters, on which account ſhe is call'd <hi>the Mother of us all;</hi> but when other Churches were form'd, that at <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> was no more the Univerſal Church; but only an integral part of it, and co-ordinate with other Churches; for its Univerſality was not of the Eſſence; but only a ſperable adjunct of it; nor did ſhe propagate theſe Churches, which afterward ſprang from her, as ſhe was Univerſal; but as ſhe was a Church. And ſo all the Churches of the Apoſtles planting, were at firſt but ſingle Congregations; yet it doth not thence follow, that every ſingle Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation is a Church. I mean, that which, in the Scripture is honour'd with the name of a Church; that is, the Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterial, Synodal, Claſſical, Dioceſan, or Collegiate Church. I would not be thought to deny to the Congregational, or (as now they are call'd) Parochial Churches, any thing, either of name, or of priviledge, that is their right; but will call them, for diſtinction ſake, Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoral Churches, and grant that they have a power of governing themſelves, as ſuch; as every Family hath a power and
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:64639:67"/>right to govern it ſelf, and every Troop and Company in an Army, by their own proper Officers within their own Sphears, and cannot be legally impos'd on by other Family-Maſters, or other Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains, with whom they are equal. But what Families are to Corporations, and theſe to Kingdoms, or Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealths; and what Troops, and parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Companies are to Regiments, and theſe to Armies; ſuch are Congregations to Churches; that is, Presbyterial Churches, and theſe to the Univerſal. I am not now concerned to ſpeak of the Church Univerſal, which is in Scripture call'd <hi>The Church;</hi> but of the Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial, which alone is that, which in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is call'd <hi>a Church,</hi> that is, a perfect and adult Church, that hath power by its Officers, to propagate and conſtitute other Churches and Congregations, and to over-rule all the particular Paſtors of the Charges and Congregations, that are within its bounds and limits. This Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterial, or Collegiate Ruling Church muſt conſiſt of a <hi>pars Regens,</hi> and a <hi>pars Regenda,</hi> all cannot be Rulers here, nor equally intereſſed in the Power of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment;
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:64639:68"/>that were <hi>Democracy,</hi> and but one little remove from <hi>Anarchy;</hi> neither can the Power reſt in one ſingle Perſon, that were abſolute <hi>Monarchy,</hi> which is the common Parent of <hi>Tyranny;</hi> but it muſt therefore be a ſelect number or <hi>Collegium</hi> of ſuch of the Presbyters, or Miniſters of the Goſpel, as are beſt qualify'd with Age, Gravity, Experience, Learning, Piety, and eſpecially Humility, Charity, Moderation and Contempt of the World, with an Holy Zeal and Diligence; which are the Qualifications the Scripture in this caſe requires. And this company of Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Presbyters in every ſuch Church, muſt have one <hi>Head,</hi> or <hi>Preſident,</hi> which is the <hi>Epiſcopus Epiſcoporum,</hi> or elſe it were a Monſter, an heap of confuſion and unor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>organiz'd matter. This Head muſt be <hi>One;</hi> elſe there can be no union nor con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtency of the parts, nor attainment of its ends. This One Head muſt be <hi>fixt</hi> and conſtant, and that in the ſame Perſon, till there be juſt cauſe to change; elſe the Government cannot be ſteddy, but is diſſolved and broken, and conſequently the Church, with all its particular Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations, moſt dangerouſly expos'd And
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:64639:68"/>this is that Government which is call'd <hi>Ariſtocracy,</hi> and may as properly be call'd a <hi>mixt or limited Monarchy;</hi> which I take to be moſt agreeable to the Pattern gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven us in the Mount of the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. And is ſo far from intrenching upon the Right, or infringing the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty or Government of the Church Congregational, that it is the beſt De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence to it, and as a ſtrong Wall about it. 'Tis true, it may be abus'd; and what is there in the World that may not? but to plead againſt any Form of Government only from the Abuſe of it, is Cavil, and not Argument.</p>
               <p>From what hath been ſaid, I conclude, that the Presbyterial and Dioceſan Church, in the Eſſentials of their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions, are one and the ſame thing. Tho' there be many Words and Names of things, that are become of ill Fame, thro' the Idolatry, Hereſie, Superſtition, Tyranny, and Immorality of a degene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Age, yet the things that are ſignified by them are, in themſelves good and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, and perhaps the very ſame that others plead for under other Names and Titles. And, could they be but once a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:64639:69"/>duly purg'd of theſe defilements, would be as glorious and uſeful, as of old they were in the Apoſtles and Primitive times. And if ever it be the good Will of God that the Church of <hi>England</hi> be once again Reform'd, in the Government and Diſcipline of it, according to Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, it muſt not be by plucking up and deſtroying that which is good; but by purging that which is foul and removing that which is burdenſom and ſuperfluous.</p>
               <p>I am ſorry to ſee, how cunningly ſome men's Logick can argue, from this Subor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination of Congregational Paſtors to Presbyterial, or Dioceſan Preſidents, or Super-intendents, a neceſſity of one Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Papal Head, and not by the ſame Rules of their Logick argue it as conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quentially neceſſary, from the Sub-ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of Officers in an Army, or Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth, that there muſt be one Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Humane Head and Monarch over all the Armies, or all the Nations in the World.</p>
               <p>I confeſs, this Chapter hath drawn out more words, than I, at firſt, thought it ſhould have done. Nor have I altogether pleas'd my ſelf in the Method of it. For
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:64639:69"/>any accidental miſtakes in the <hi>Manner</hi> of expreſſing my intended ſenſe, I beg the pardon of my more critical Reader. But if any thing, on calm and impartial exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination, appear, in the <hi>Matter</hi> of it, He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terodox to the Truth reveal'd and taught us in the Holy Scriptures, I ſhall readily acknowledge my errour, and not take it as a ſhame to be made wiſer.</p>
               <p>The ſum of what I have herein aim'd at, I ſhall now wind up in theſe eight Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>Poſit. I. <hi>that our LORD Jeſus Chriſt hath not left his Church in the World, without a proper Government, of his own appointment for it.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Poſ. II. <hi>That this Government is to be ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naged for, and under him, and by his Laws and Authority, by thoſe into whoſe hands he hath delivered the</hi> Keys.</item>
                  <item>Poſ. III. <hi>That Ruling Elders, diſtinct from all Preaching Elders and Deacons, are no Divine Ordinance in the Church of God, now under the New Teſtament.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Poſ. IV. <hi>That every Paſtor, lawfully or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain'd, and call'd to the Charge of a particular Congregation, hath a Divine
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:64639:70"/>Right of executing the whole Office of a Paſtor in and over that Congregation.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Poſ. V. <hi>That every Paſtor of a Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as ſuch, is under the governing power of that Claſſical Presbytery, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of he is, or ought to be a Member.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Poſ. VI. <hi>That the Claſſical, or Dioceſan Presbytery ought to be but a ſelect num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, and not the whole Body of that Claſſis, or Dioceſs.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Poſ. VII. <hi>That the Form and Power of Ruling Presbyteries ought to be fixt and conſtant, and not occaſional only and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termittent.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Poſ. VIII. <hi>That every Claſſical Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ought to have a ſingle Head or Preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, and which ought to be continued in that Office,</hi> quam diu bene ſe geſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit.</item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <pb n="132" facs="tcp:64639:70"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CAP. VI.</hi> A few words of Counſel and Incourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to the Lambs, the younger ſort.</head>
               <p>I Am now come to the laſt part of my preſent Task; to ſpeak a little to the Flock, over which our LORD hath ſet us; and</p>
               <p n="1">1. Will begin, as he himſelf hath taught me, with the <hi>Lambs:</hi> And O that I could now pour out my Soul into their boſoms, and offer ſomething that may awaken and engage their chaſt affections to an early and ſerious minding of Chriſt, and of their own Souls! I am not ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to thoſe, who thro' want of years are uncapable, but to ſuch as are able to apprehend the words and counſels of God from the Pulpit, or the Preſs. My dear Lambs, you ſee what care our LORD Jeſus Chriſt hath taken of you.</p>
               <p n="1">1. He calls you <hi>His,</hi> what an Honour, what a Happineſs is this? If you be his,
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:64639:71"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="132" facs="tcp:64639:71"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="132" facs="tcp:64639:72"/>he will be yours, yours to all gracious ends and purpoſes; yours to love you, yours to provide for you, yours to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tect you, yours to bleſs, to guide, to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct, to own, to ſanctifie, to ſave you. He will be a Friend, a Father, a Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, an All, and better than all to you. Let who will forſake you, your God is unchangeable, he will never for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake you; yea, when all others forſake, then will he be every way beſt to you; you ſhall never want a Friend, while you have a Friend in Heaven. But re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member, you cannot be ſo <hi>His,</hi> nor He <hi>Yours,</hi> without your voluntary, hearty, unreſerved ſelf-dedication to him. He will not be yours, without your delibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate choice, and free and full conſent. If he be yours, it muſt be by Covenant, and by a Covenant of Salt, you muſt be his Covenant-Servants, and that for ever. He that putteth his hand to Gods Plough muſt not look back. Yea, you muſt be ſo his, as to be no more your own. If Chriſt be yours, he muſt be your LORD to rule and command you; his Will muſt be your Will, and his Word your Rule, and his Work your delight. O
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:64639:72"/>that this may help now to oblige and incourage you to offer your firſt, your beſt, your Bodies, your Souls, your all to the LORD!</p>
               <p n="2">2. He calls upon his <hi>Lambs.</hi> The Lambs are the Hope of the Flock, and the Joy of the Shepherd. None ſo wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come to him, as thoſe that ſeek him be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, that devote the firſt fruits of their youth, and ſtrength, and affections to him. It was <hi>John,</hi> the youngeſt Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciple that was the beloved one. <hi>I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member thee, the kindneſs of thy youth, the love of thine eſpouſals, Jer.</hi> 2.2. Sirs, this is the day of your Viſitation, <hi>behold now is the accepted time <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus complacentiae, &amp; gratuitae receptionis: Behold now is the Day of Salvation.</hi> This is your ſeaſon, the day of Gods ſpecial Grace; which is true, not only of the day of the Goſpel in general, but eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially of the day of youth; this is the day of your greateſt advantage, on very many accounts. Now is your time to lay the Foundations of your future Eternal happineſs. If you loſe this Seaſon, you are, for ought you know, loſt for ever. If you now be before hand with the
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:64639:73"/>Tempter, you will the more eaſily have him under your feet as long as you live. <hi>I have written unto you young men,</hi> ſays the Apoſtle, <hi>becauſe ye are strong, and have o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vercome the wicked one,</hi> 1 <hi>John</hi> 2.13, 14. if you do not now overcome him, you will be worſe able to do it hereafter. As the Enemy grows ſtronger, you will find your ſelves grow weaker; yea, the more calls of God you reject in your youth, the nearer you are to that Curſe, <hi>Prov.</hi> 29.1. <hi>He that being often reproved hardeneth his neck, ſhall ſuddenly be deſtroyed, and that without remedy.</hi> O do not preſume on the leiſure of Old Age! how many thouſands are there that once refuſed to give God their youth, that are now ſpending their wretched old age in Hell? 'Tis as damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble a piece of Atheiſm as any, to account the dregs of our time and ſtrength good enough for God, and for our own Souls. Be not deceived; tho' there were ſome called at the ninth, and at the eleventh hour, they were only ſuch as had not been called before. Certainly 'tis a moſt dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous, and almoſt deſperate adventure to neglect the offers of Grace that are made in the days of youth. And O what care
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:64639:73"/>ſhould you now take, how you lay your foundations! Youth is in this reſpect, the moſt critical part of our lives; as the foundation is that is then laid, ſuch is the ſuperſtructure like to be. O 'twill be hard plucking up old Foundations, when once they are ſetled! What is begun in Hypocriſie, is wont to end in Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtacy. Let not that reproachful Proverb be verifi'd in you, to the ſhame of your Profeſſion, and the eternal ruine of your own Souls, <hi>Young Saints, and old Devils.</hi> If your firſt works be not ſound as to the Principles both of Faith and Love, your end is like to be very ſad and ſhameful. My dear Lambs! are you Chriſts? how ſhould this oblige you to carry your ſelves, in all things, as becomes your relation to him? Hath he pick'd and choſen you out of the World, and ſet his love upon you, and made a differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence between you, and others? O do not walk, nor talk, nor attire your ſelves then like the vain ones of the World! if the difference between you and others, as to your Spiritual Eſtates be real, let it be viſible too in your Carriage and whole Converſation. <hi>As obedient Children, not
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:64639:74"/>faſhioning your ſelves according to the for me luſts in your ignorance.</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 7.14. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>; not decking and moding your ſelves according to the humours and manners of thoſe, whoſe luſts are their rule, and whoſe exalted heads do but proclaim the folly and pride of their hearts. O let not Chriſt's lambs be the world's apes! Let the world <hi>behold your chaſt converſation coupled with fear,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.2. The 7th <hi>Commandment</hi> is violated by the unchaſtity of habit and geſture, as well as by words or actions: there is a whoriſh Attire, as well as a whoriſh eye and a whoriſh tongue, and a whoriſh heart. 'Tis not enough for Chriſt's lambs, not to be ſuch, but they muſt not be like them. <hi>Abſtain from all ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance of evil,</hi> 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.22. <hi>Hating even the garment ſpotted by the fleſh,</hi> Jud. 23. As the <hi>Menſtruous Garment</hi> was ceremonially un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clean under the Law, ſo is the <hi>Meretrici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Garment</hi> much more ſpiritually, or mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally unclean under the <hi>Goſpel; Whoſe ador<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning let it not be that outward adorning of pleating the hair, and of wearing of gold, and of putting on of apparel; but let it he the hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den man of the heart, in that which is not cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptible, even the ornament of a meek and quiet
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:64639:74"/>ſpirit, which is in the ſight of God of great price,</hi> 1 Pet. 3.3, 4. I do not think that the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> doth here declaim againſt the uſe of theſe things, nor that he doth adviſe that Chriſtians, or Profeſſors ſhould have a mode or faſhion in their Apparel diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent from all others. Cloathing is appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of God, not only for covering, but for decency and ornament, and for diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of Sexes and Callings, and degrees amongſt men; but he forbids and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demns that immoderate care, and coſt, and carioſity that is uſed in theſe things, to the neglect of the better part, which is of infinitely higher concern: And he for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bids too, their imitating and ſymbolizing with the world in the cuts and faſhions, and gallantry of their immodeſt pride and vanity; as the Lord did of old for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid his people to be like the <hi>Idolatrous Heathen,</hi> in the trimings of their <hi>heads</hi> and <hi>Beards,</hi> Levit. 19.27. <hi>Ye ſhall not round the corners of your heads; neither ſhalt thou mar the corners of thy beard.</hi> Not but that this faſhion was in it ſelfindifferent, but becauſe it was the manner of the Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous Nations, and particularly of the <hi>Egyptians,</hi> from whom he had now deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:64639:75"/>them; therefore he would not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer his <hi>Iſrael</hi> to be herein like them. 'Tis not ſimply the faſhion, but the height and extremity of it, wherein the pride and levity, and conſequently the ſin doth lye.</p>
               <p>I am loth to raiſe Objections for you; but perhaps you have heard ſome that are willing to plead for this Idol, ſay, that there is evidently as great a pride in thoſe, that are at the wideſt diſtance from the Modes and Faſhions of the Times, as in thoſe that are fondeſt of them. It may be ſo; but alas, is this Argument, or Recrimination? How un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable is it to think to juſtify the pride, and ſin of one extream by that of another? Or, would you ſay, That you have herein the Example of many very pious, ferious and knowing Chriſtians? I ſhall only reply thus; The more pity. But that which I doubt more of, is this; You are afraid you ſhall be cenſur'd and talk'd of; yet how poor a thing is this? let thoſe that will laugh at you now, laugh if they can at laſt, when you ſhall ſtand on the right hand, and they on the left. But he or ſhe that can't bear a
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:64639:75"/>flout, or a jear, or ſcorn for <hi>Chriſt,</hi> from the Fools of the World; that will not be perſwaded to part with a pin, or a rag for him, is very unworthy of him. O let not the Daughters, nor the Sons of <hi>Zion,</hi> in ſuch a day as this, wherein God hath been ſo long, and ſo many ways humbling us; when his hand is lifted up, and his Sword drawn, and bath'd in the blood of the ſlain; when he is ſo loudly calling us to Sackcloth and Aſhes, and deep humilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, tempt him to execute the Threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings of <hi>Iſa.</hi> 3. upon the Wantons of this Generation. Let not the <hi>Foreheads,</hi> that ſhould be mark'd with weeping and mourning, be mark'd with the provoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of divine indignation.</p>
               <p n="3">3. He hath charg'd us <hi>to feed his Lambs.</hi> And in obedience to his commands, and compaſſion to your ſouls, we are willing, and always ready to draw out our Breaſts to you. O how pleaſant is it to ſuckle our little ones! what a comfort is it to hear you enquiring after God, and asking us the ferious queſtions, that ſavour of a work of grace upon your hearts! How doth this endear you to us, and make us even proud of you? of whom we may ſay, as
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:64639:76"/>the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> of his beloved <hi>Theſſalonians, Eph.</hi> 2.19, 20. <hi>For what is our hope, or joy, or crown of rejoycing, are not even ye, in the preſence of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt at his coming? For ye are our glory, I ſay.</hi> 'Tis a comfort to us to hear you ſo readily and cheerfully anſwering our queſtions, in what you have learnt, either from your Catechiſes, or from our Sermons; but it would be a greater comfort to us to anſwer your Queſtions; either for the information and rectifying of your Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; the regulation of your Practice, or the ſatisfaction of your doubting Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences. By this we ſhould ſee how you grow and improve in the Faith, and that our Labours with, and for you, are not in vain in the Lord.</p>
               <p n="4">4. He hath charg'd us, <hi>as we love him'</hi> to have an eſpecial care of you. May not this aſſure you how dear you are to him? and ſhould not this both engage, and encourage you in your work? My dear Children, 'Tis our love to Chriſt, and to your ſouls, that alone is able to ſweeten our work to us. Tho we travel in birth again with you, till Chriſt be formed in you, yet never did your Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:64639:76"/>more willingly endure the pains of their Travel for you, nor more joyfully embrace you, from the Womb of the natural birth, than we would do from the Womb of the New-birth. As there is joy in a Family at the living birth of a Son, or of a Daughter, ſo there is joy both in Heaven above, and in the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven of the Church here below, at the converſion of a ſinner unto God. O let us ſhare in this heavenly joy over you, and be able to ſay, in the day of his coming; <hi>Behold, we, and the children whom the Lord hath given us.</hi> But I muſt not inſiſt here.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VII.</hi> The Peoples Duty.</head>
               <p>BEar with me while I ſpeak a few words to thoſe whom I mean by the Sheep; the more adult, and aged ſort of profeſſors: Which I ſhall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prize as briefly as I can, in theſe ſix Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars.</p>
               <pb n="142" facs="tcp:64639:77"/>
               <p n="1">1. Doth Chriſt own you for his <hi>Sheeps</hi> Should not you then own him for your <hi>Shepherd?</hi> And if ſo, ſhould you not know his voice, and be able to diſcern it from the voice of a ſtranger? Sirs, your Shepherd is but one, tho your inferior Paſtors and Teachers be many, and his voice in them all is one and the ſame: If they ſpeak not with his Voice, they are not of his ſending. There are many Thieves and Robbers in the world, that come in Sheeps clothing, and wear a rough garment to deceive; and many there are that are deceived by them: 'T was ſo from the beginning, ever ſince Satan hath transform'd himſelf into an Angel of Light; and ſo it will ever be, 'till he be bound, and caſt into the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomleſs pit. But thoſe that are his, know his voice, and a Stranger will they not follow. This is one of the <hi>Propria quarto modo</hi> of his Sheep; they have an <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nction from the holy one, and know all things;</hi> that is, all things that are abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely neceſſary to ſalvation. Not that they are infallible, as to the Circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tials, and leſſer matters of Religion; herein they may be, and too often are
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:64639:77"/>deceived. Hence are thoſe diverſities of opinion that are among them, and thoſe ſcandalous unbrotherly diſſentions, that are the effects of them: But this di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity is not in the Shepherd's Voice, but in their apprehenſions, and the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of their capacities, and attainments: But the more perfectly the Shepherd's Voice is known, the leſs there will be of this diverſity of apprehenſion and ſtrife about it. And yet this variety of opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in the Circumſtantials, would hardly deſerve to be accounted a blemiſh in the myſtical body, were it not for that ſelfiſhneſs, that is commonly the root, and that uncharitableneſs, that is the fruit of it. But beſides this, it is ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and ſad to conſider, how many there be, that have been all their lives, even to old age flock'd and folded a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Sheep of Chriſt, under the ſame ordinances, and ſpiritual enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments with others, and yet underſtand very little of the Shepherds voice, that are ever learning, <hi>and never able to come to the knowledge of the truth,</hi> 2 Tim. 3.7. That for want of Principles, are like children toſſed to and fro, and carried
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:64639:78"/>away with every wind of Doctrine; or whoſe minds are like ſieves, that retain nothing, but the earthly groſſer ſort of things. <hi>Who for the time, ought to be Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, but yet have need that one teach them again, which be the firſt Principles of the Oracles of God, Heb.</hi> 5.12. Such Sheep are the ſhame of ſuch a Shepherd.</p>
               <p>Again; If you are his Sheep, ſhould you not hear, and hearken to his Voice, and delight in his Preſence with you? Should you not come at his Call, and go at his Bidding, and his Word be a Law with you? <hi>My Sheep hear my Voice, and I know them, and they follow me, Joh.</hi> 10.27.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Is he your <hi>Shepherd?</hi> O how ſhould you <hi>love him</hi> then? 'Tis natural for Sheep to love their Shepherd; but though in this caſe, it be indeed ſupernatural, yet it is, of all things in the World, the moſt reaſonable. He is not only your Shepherd, to feed, and to protect, and provide; but your Saviour, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer, to die for you. <hi>I am the good Shepherd; the good Shepherd giveth his life for the Sheep, Joh.</hi> 10.11. We muſt have periſht eternally, but for him. 'Twere endleſs to enumerate all the reaſons we
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:64639:78"/>have to love him; which way ſoever we look upon him, in his Perſon, in his Offices, in his Graces; in what he hath done, in what he hath ſuffered, in what he hath purchaſed, in what he hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed, in what he hath prepared for us; he is altogether lovely. Yea, as the Sun is all Light; ſo is Chriſt all Love to his Saints. His Word are his Love-Letters to them; his Ordinances his Love-Feaſts with them; and all his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidences, both Croſſes and Comforts, are the Seals of his Love to them. The more we ſeriouſly think of him, or of our ſelves; the more we ſhall ſee it both reaſonable and neceſſary to love him. We cannot love our ſelves truly, unleſs we love him ſincerely. <hi>If any man love not the LORD Jeſus Chriſt, let him be Anathema Maranatha,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 16.22. One of the moſt accurſed Wretches, that are out of Hell. <hi>O love the LORD, all ye his Saints; for the LORD preſerveth the faithful, and plentifully rewardeth the proud doer, Pſal.</hi> 31.23. 'Tis our Duty; 'tis our Intereſt; and, if we are Saints in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, 'tis our Property to love him. God is Love; where there is moſt of
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:64639:79"/>Love, there is moſt of God, and moſt of a Chriſtian. Where Love dwells, there God dwells; and where God is, there is Heaven. The glorified Life above is a Life of perfect Love. Love will make you a Heaven upon Earth; a Heaven of Holineſs, and a Heaven of Joy and Peace. O in what holy Order is every thing kept, in that heart, where the Love of Chriſt reigns! every inordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate Affection, and irregular Paſſion ſuppreſt; every Temptation eaſily re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted and repelled; the whole Frame and Oeconomy of the Soul under the power and ſweet Influences of Love. And O the heavenly Peace and Serenity that is there! what a calm is there, where the Love of Chriſt commands all! What a Banquet of Spiritual Joy is that Soul feaſting on with her Beloved! her heart is at reſt in him; all the burden of her cares and fears are devolved upon him; the poor Soul rides ſafely at An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chor, and is careful for nothing. O Sirs! 'Tis not ſo where the Love of the World, and the Luſts of the Fleſh rule; there's the Hell of vile affections, ſpiritual filthineſs, ungodly counſel, and courſes:
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:64639:79"/>There are the ſtorms and tempeſts, the reſtleſs, foaming waves of carnal deſires, and worldly cares, and fears, and fretful diſcontents: 'Tis a miſerable life that the worldling lives. <hi>The wicked are like the troubled Sea, when it cannot reſt, whoſe waters cast up mire and dirt, Iſa.</hi> 57.20. And 'tis our ſin and folly, that we are ſo like them. The Love of Chriſt would help all this. Yea, do you not profeſs to love him? and would you not be offend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with him that ſhould queſtion it? But what is Profeſſion without proof? If you love him, you will obey him, and none of his Commandments will be grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous to you. Love is bountiful; nothing will be too much, or too dear for him: The Love that is genuine, is generous, If you love him, you will love all of him. his Image, his Company, his Ordinances, his Miniſters, his Ways. But I muſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer you to others, for the Marks of the Sincerity of your Love to him.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Are you his <hi>Sheep?</hi> Should you not then <hi>love one another?</hi> The Sheep is a ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciable creature, extreamly fond of their fellows. O let not Chriſt's Sheep be Wolves and Tygers to one another. <hi>A
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:64639:80"/>new Commandment I give you, that ye love one another, as I have loved you; that ye alſo love one another;</hi> Joh. 13.34. <hi>Be ye followers of God, as dear Children, and walk in love, as Chriſt hath loved us, and hath given himſelf for us;</hi> Epheſ. 5.1, 2. <hi>See that ye love one another with a pure heart fervently;</hi> 1 Pet. 1.22. <hi>We know that we have paſſed from death into life, becauſe we love the Brethren. He that loveth not his Brother abideth in death;</hi> 1 Joh. 3.14. There hath been enough ſpoken and written on this Subject. One of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moneſt Themes, of a moſt contentious Age. But alas! words are wind, and the wind hath but blown the Coals. And Love is no <hi>Salamander;</hi> it cannot live in the Fire; yea, though it be it ſelf a fire, it is from above, of another nature and original, whoſe flame will not unite, nor conſpire with thoſe heterogeneous ſmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers which are from beneath. How par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial and private-ſpirited is the Charity of moſt of the hotteſt Zealots in every Party? that cannot overcome the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judices of their Ignorance, Intereſt or Education; but with pettiſh <hi>Jonah,</hi> think they do well to be angry. O that men
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:64639:80"/>knew better what ſpirit they are of. The Flock of Chriſt are not all of one com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexion, nor of one Drove, nor of one manner of Diſcipline in Circumſtantials. Thoſe that have many Sheep, have ſome fat, and ſome lean; ſome that are kept more ſtrictly in their fenced Fields, others that feed and range at greater liberty, on the courſe, and cold, and ſhort Downs, and Commons; yet have they all but one common Nature, one Name, one Mark, and one Maſter. So it is with the Flock of Chriſt in this their imperfect ſtate: There are ſome that are not ſo clean, nor ſo ſound as others; yet they are Sheep, and his Sheep, and muſt, as ſuch, be loved and pitied, and not hated, or ſcorned, or diſowned by us. I have ſometimes wondered at the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, why Diſſentions on Religious ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts are always wont to be moſt fierce and implacable: It cannot be becauſe Man, in this his lapſed eſtate, is ſo Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious a Creature; no, 'tis the Enemy that hath the moſt deep and miſchievous Deſign in it; 'tis Pride, and Envy, and Superſtition, that is the <hi>Fomes</hi> of the Mine, to which the Devil lays his Train,
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:64639:81"/>under colour of Religion, to blow up Religion, and all that depends upon it in the World. The Enemy fears not much what hurt Religion can do his intereſt in the world, if he can but blow up the cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of thoſe that profeſs it: For what doth Faith ſignify without love, by which it works?</p>
               <p n="4">4. Are you his Sheep? ſhould you not then be very tender of your own Lambs? There is hardly any kind of Creature, but is fond of their young; and if in any caſe they will be fierce, 'tis in their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence. <hi>Even the Sea Monſters draw out the breaſts, they give ſuck to their young ones,</hi> Lam. 4.3. O let not thoſe that are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Chriſtians, be like the <hi>Oſtriches</hi> in the <hi>Wilderneſs,</hi> and forget that their poor Children have ſouls as well as bodies to be cared for. Thoſe that are evil know how to give good gifts to their Children. They know how to feed them when they are hungry; how to cloath them when they are naked; how to phyſick them when they are ſick; how to inſtruct them in their worldly buſineſs, and how to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow them for their worldly advantage: And herein there are few ſo unnatural,
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:64639:81"/>but that they are diligent enough accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their ability and underſtanding; and if this be all you do for yours, what do ye more than others: You rejoice perhaps in that they are born, and you can call them yours, but what can you hope for from them? what comfort can you promiſe your ſelves in them, if they be not new born? If you provide only for their bodies, their baſer and mortal part, what do you for them more than for your Hogs, or Cattel, which you are careful to feed, and make fat for the day of ſlaughter? Can you without terror think of their being damn'd? Should you not do your utmoſt then to prevent it? Do you not know that they are by Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture the Children of Wrath? And that you were the Inſtruments of bringing them into this condition? Are you not bound in Juſtice then, with all your Care and Diligence to endeavour their Deliverance? How can you believe this, and not be concerned for them? 'Tis true, we your Paſtors are bound by the command of Chriſt to feed them; but are not you equally bound both by the Bonds of Grace and Nature, to begin,
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:64639:82"/>and to aſſiſt with us in that work? Time forbids me, tho' my bowels urge me to enlarge here. O let not Reformation dye, at half way, with this Generation; but let what we have ſtriven, and pray'd, and ſuffered, and ſo long waited for, be, by Gods bleſſing on your faithful diligence, and utmoſt endeavours conveyed, with advantage, to the next. Tho God can, of Stones, raiſe up Children unto <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> yet you may not expect, that he ſhall work Miracles for thoſe, that live in the neglect of known duty.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Are you his Sheep, and commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by him, who is both our LORD and Maſter and yours, to us, to feed and to rule for him? Should you not then <hi>heark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en to us,</hi> and own the authority, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with we are entruſted for your good? Remember, we muſt give our accounts ſhortly, and ſo muſt you. Whether e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver I ſhall meet you again in this Place, God knows; but am ſure, that we ſhall one day meet again in a far greater aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly than this. When the ſight of them that have here, or elſewhere, la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boured with and for you, will be either very comfortable, or unexpreſſibly ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible,
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:64639:82"/>on the account of the Teſtimony, that muſt then be produced by them, either for or againſt you. 'Tis true, we are not Lords over you, nor do we pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend ſo to be; yet are we appointed of Chriſt to be your Officers, not only to teach, admoniſh, reprove, rebuke, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hort, and encourage you; but to lead, and rule, and govern, to warn, and charge and command you in the LORD, in all things that concern our Office. If eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry tranſgreſſion and diſobedience, under the Law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> received a juſt recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſe of reward, can you hope to eſcape under the Goſpel? Sirs, it hath been for your ſakes, that we have endur'd the contradictions of men; have been eject<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, deprived, baniſhed, impriſon'd revil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and wherein you your ſelves have ſuffered with us; yet all this we have born with patience, and deſire from our Hearts to forgive and forget; but O let not your hands be now againſt us; this will be worſe, and harder to be born, than all the evil that hath befallen us from our youth, nor can you hope that it will be taken well by our common LORD and Maſter. While we were
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:64639:83"/>removed into corners with you, we ſeem'd to be very dear to you; but, let me tell you, if you once more provoke him to remove us, he will, I doubt put us farther from you, where you ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſee us more. If your Liberty be a Snare to you, you may expect that God ſhall, to your ſorrow, break this Snare for you. We have been your Servants, and ſo we are ſtill, and delight to be, the Servants of your Faith; but God forbid, that any thing ſhould ever tempt us to be the Servants of your Luſts, or of your evil humours; this we are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quir'd to declare and proteſt againſt, and to exerciſe the Rod of Evangelical Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline; for our LORD hath put the <hi>Keys</hi> of his Kingdom, and <hi>Rod</hi> of his Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment into our hands, to rule under him, and for him, in the affairs of your Souls; the Government is <hi>His,</hi> and not <hi>Ours;</hi> if you will not that this man ſhall Reign over you; if you will yet kick at his Yoke, and break his bonds; look to it, for, evil is before you. <hi>O give glory to the LORD your God before he cauſe Darkneſs, and before your Feet ſtumble on the dark Mountains, and while ye look for light, he turn
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:64639:83"/>it into the Shadow of Death, and make it groſs darkneſs. But if ye will not hear it, my Soul ſhall weep in ſecret places for your Pride, and mine Eye ſhall weep ſore, Jer.</hi> 13 16, 17. But I hope God will have mercy yet, for his own ſake, upon the Remnant of his Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and will at length bow their Hearts to the obedience of the Goſpel.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Once more; Are you his Sheep, whom he hath committed to our Paſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral care? Let me tell you, <hi>We ſhall not, we cannot, be with you always.</hi> Your Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, where are they? And the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, do they live for ever? There are enough, you know, that wiſh the World were rid of us, in whoſe account we are the troublers of <hi>Iſrael.</hi> It would ſend our Gray Hairs with ſorrow to the Grave, to think with whom we ſhould leave theſe few Sheep in this Wilderneſs, were there not a proſpect of a Succeſſion. You know where the Curſe of <hi>Eli</hi>'s Houſe lies; <hi>Put me, I pray thee, into one of the Prieſts Offices, that I may eat a piece of Bread.</hi> But where there is no Prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, there is no Ambition. There are few that offer themſelves with us, to the work of the Houſe of the LORD,
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:64639:84"/>but thoſe that have nothing but an Heart, and a good Will to offer. And indeed, theſe are they, may we but have enough of theſe, that are moſt likely to do Gods Work. Had Avarice and Ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion never found any ſuch thing, as a Bait, or Temptation of this kind, in this Sacred Office, further than the double Honour, that is due to double Merits, it might have been much happier with the Churches, than now it is. 'Twas World<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Riches and Grandeur, which the Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy, of all men in the World, are worſt able to bear, as that which is moſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuitable to the Nature of their Holy Calling, that was the great Engine; which thro' the Pride and Covetouſneſs of Prelates, and the blind Zeal and Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition of Princes and Bigots, firſt overthrew both the Purity and the Peace of the Churches. Nor is the Fire ever like to go out, while the fewel holds. But God hath delivered us from this Temptation; and perhaps this is not the leaſt of the Mercies we have to bleſs him for; at leaſt, if he have taught us there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with to be content, and to live by Faith for our daily Bread. But when we are
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:64639:84"/>laid in the Duſt, as ſhortly we ſhall, who are they that ſhall fill our Places? God will provide, but not from among the Dead, nor by Miracle. You know on whoſe Pious Zeal and Ability, under God, this Succeſſion neceſſarily depends. If then you be not weary of us as of your Burden; if you account us faithful, and ſerviceable; that our Light and Labours among you have been of any good Uſe, or Value, to ſave you hitherto from that black Night of Superſtition and Idolatry, that hath ſo long hover'd over us; And if this be a bleſſing, that you would en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tail to your Poſterities after you; then ſet your Hearts and Hands to this Work, and lay out ſomething, to your power, as God hath bleſſed you, and as you hope for his bleſſing, for the Souls of your Children and Survivors, tho' you ſhould (and yet you have no reaſon to doubt you ſhall) have the leſs to lay up for their pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing part. O Sirs, 'tis for Chriſt's and for your lakes, that we have deny'd our ſelves, as we have done; had we aim'd at our worldly advantage, and taken up the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry for a Lively-hood, we were of all men in the World, ſome of the moſt mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaken
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:64639:85"/>and worſt advis'd; we might eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly have found other ways enough, to have beſtow'd our time, and ſtrength and learning on, to better purpoſe that way; but in the ſervice of your Souls we are ready to Sacrifice theſe our Worldly In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſts and hope that you will never give us cauſe to repent of it. And if we have laid down our all at your feet; it is but reaſonable and juſt, that you ſhould lay down ſomething, as the primitive Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians did, at the Apoſtle's Feet, for the neceſſary Uſe, and Service of the Church; that ſo when we, who are now grown old, and going out of the Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard, ſhall dye, that which you now profeſs to prize as your Priviledge and Happineſs, may not dye with us. 'Tis for your ſakes, and not my own, that I have now mentioned this thing.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CAP. VIII.</hi> The Conſolatory Concluſion.</head>
               <p>I Shall now conclude all, with a word of <hi>incouragement,</hi> both to Miniſters, and People,</p>
               <pb n="159" facs="tcp:64639:85"/>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>To Miniſters;</hi> and that on a double account.</p>
               <p n="1">1. In that God hath accounted us faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, and put us into the Miniſtry, and called us unto this Heavenly work, than which there is none greater, none ſweeter in the World. That he hath taken us ſo near to him, and entruſted us with the Bread of his Family, the care of his Children, and all the precious Jewels of his Houſe, the unſearchable Riches of Chriſt. O what an honour is this! that poor, deſpiſed, unworthy we, ſhould be called, not the Sons of God only, but the Stewards, the Ambaſſadours, the Angels of the Moſt High; that we ſhould be taken into ſo near a relation to him, made the keepers of his Counſels, his Treaſurers, his Oratours and Interceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſours, the deputed Governours of his Spiritual Kingdom in the World. Behold what manner of love is this, what a hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs, what a Priviledge is it? There are ſome of us, who, for ought we know, had never been ſincerely and ſavingly ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, had not our Holy Calling given us the bleſſed occaſion. How had we been buried in the dirty buſineſs, and
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:64639:86"/>cares and ſnares of the World, had not the LORD ſet his merciful eye upon us, and choſen us to walk with him? What were we better than the reſt of Mankind? what hath he foreſeen in any of us, that he ſhould make this difference? Bleſſed be Chriſt Jeſus our dear LORD for this, Be it hard, yet 'tis happy work. <hi>I had rather be a Door-Keeper in the Houſe of my God, than to dwell in the Tents of wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs;</hi> rather a Porter there, than a Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentate in the Earth. The Church is Gods lower Heaven as contemptible as it is in the eyes of blind and prejudiced Men; and the loweſt place in this Heaven is, on many accounts, preferrable to the higheſt Worldly Seats among the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of Men.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Hath our LORD and Maſter taken care for his Lambs, and for his Sheep, and will he not alſo care for us? Muſt we feed his Flock and will not He feed us? Hath he not done it for theſe 30 years &amp; more, and that beyond what we had any viſible grounds to have hoped? <hi>When I ſent you without Purſe and Scrip, and Shoes, lacked ye any thing? Luke</hi> 22.35. When there were ſo few that would adventure to know us, and fewer that could relieve
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:64639:86"/>us; did we want our daily Bread? Tho' our Tables were not ſpread, as once they had been, yet were they ever ſweeter to us than then? In our Exilements, in our Priſons, was not our God with us ſtill? When we were walking thro' the valley of the Shadow of death, did not his Rod and his Staff comfort us? yea, when was it better with us than when we had leaſt of the World? and after all this ſenſible experience, ſhall we not truſt him? Fear not, he that will have his Sheep fed, will not have his Shepherds ſtarved. The World hath ſeen the effect of our <hi>Water</hi> and <hi>Pulſe,</hi> let them ſtill ſee that we can be content with a little, that we have not taught the Doctrine of contentment to others, further than we are willing to practice it our ſelves. And O that nothing that hath the appearance of a covetous or ambitious humour may ever be found any more in any of us. Let our Maſters work be our grand concern, and then we know we have reaſon to truſt him for all theſe little things.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>To the People:</hi> With what confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of Faith, and gladneſs of heart may you even in this Wilderneſs, ſing <hi>David</hi>'s
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:64639:87"/>
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 23. <hi>The Lord is my Shepherd, I ſhall not want.</hi> The Charge here given in my Text was, and is intended to run parallel with all ſucceeding ages. As long as Chriſt hath a Flock in the World, he will find or make thoſe that ſhall feed it: Let the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy ſhow his skill, and the gates of hell do their worſt, there's never a ſoul of Chriſt's purchaſing ſhall periſh. He would not have bid you to pray the Lord of the Harveſt to ſend forth Labourers into his Harveſt, had he not a mind to anſwer thoſe Prayers. Only remember; he that hath taught and encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rag'd you ſo to pray, expects that you ſhall ſecond your Prayers with your beſt Endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours. You may not hope that God ſhall ſend you Labourers our of Heaven at free coſt; but your hands muſt evidence the good agreement between your hearts and lips, in theſe your Prayers. 'Tis for the Elects ſake that the World continues to this day, and while God hath a world here, he will have a people in it; and unto whom he will always provide thoſe that ſhall break the bread of Life; tho he may, and ſomtimes ſees it good to diſtreſs, yet will he never deſert them: He may free 'em, but will never forſake them, never forget them. <hi>Comfort ye one another with theſe words.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
